<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The antithelemite, or, An answer to certain quaeres by the D. of B. and the considerations of an unknown author concerning toleration</title>
            <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1359</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3722</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13675328</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13675328</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101227</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50329)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101227)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 794:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The antithelemite, or, An answer to certain quaeres by the D. of B. and the considerations of an unknown author concerning toleration</title>
                  <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Henry Maurice.  Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>"This may be printed. June 12, 1685; R.L.S."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Buckingham, George Villiers, --  Duke of, 1628-1687. --  Short discourse upon the reasonableness of men's having a religion.</term>
               <term>Toleration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101227:1"/>
            <p>THE Antithelemite, OR AN ANSWER To Certain QUAERES By the D. of B. And to the Conſiderations of an unknown Author CONCERNING TOLERATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This may be Printed,</hi> June 12. 1685. <hi>R.L.S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Prince's Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101227:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101227:2"/>
            <p>HIS Majeſties Gracious Declaration to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Government in Church and State as by Law Eſtabliſh'd, and the Opinion all good men have of the Affection of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to thoſe Laws by which the Proteſtant Religion is fenc'd on every ſide, may ſeem to render the Labour of a private hand on their behalf uſeleſs and ſuperfluous. Yet ſince ſome have openly, others in diſguiſe invaded theſe Fences, and proceeded to that degree of Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to recommend the Attempt to the Parliament now Aſſembled; it may be expected perhaps that thoſe who enjoy the Protection of thoſe Laws, ſhould not leave them all defenceleſs under the odious Imputation of Injuſtice and Cruelty, to depend merely upon the Authority of their firſt Eſtabliſhment, and the Favour of the Preſent Government: Our Adverſaries would then be thought juſtly to conclude, that we deſpaired of the merit of our Cauſe, and of approving it by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the Judgment of any Impartial man. Therefore I have endeavoured in this Treatiſe, to ſhew the Vanity of thoſe Cavils, (for I ſhould be guilty of too much Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, ſhould I give them the ſtyle of Reaſon or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,) againſt the Proſecution of Diſſenters according to Law. And though there ſhould be no great ſin, or publick inconvenience in a General Toleration, yet the Pleas that recommend it, are ſo mean, that they who might not be afraid, might yet be aſham'd to allow it upon ſuch miſerable motives.</p>
            <p>Yet I. muſt confeſs that the Advocates for Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101227:3"/>have one conſiderable Advantage in this Diſpute, that they are on the popular part of the Queſtion, and the ſeeming good nature of the Plea, without much reaſoning, is ſufficient to recommend it: Whereas, all Puniſhment is odious to the People, and neither Law, nor Reaſon, nor Neceſſity, can perfectly reconcile them to it. It is madneſs then to endeavour to perſuade men out of their Humanity, that is, out of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and he truly deſerves the utmoſt ſeverity that can take delight in it: What ſhall we do then? Shall we give up the Cauſe, and Subſcribe to a Toleration? Nothing leſs, and that becauſe in our Circumſtances, it is not only contrary to Religion, and Civil Prudence, but alſo to Charity and Compaſſion; it is not always Mercy to Indulge, nor Cruelty to Inflict Puniſhment: Unleſs we conclude, that a Father who corrects his Child has not ſo much tenderneſs for him as a Stranger, or a Servant that intercedes for his Pardon. But if Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency muſt take place, why ſhould not the Publick challenge it in the firſt place? and why ſhould they be judged merciful, who to humour and indulge one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would, expoſe a whole Nation to Confuſion and Ruin? If this be tender Mercy, it is that the Scripture brands with the name of Cruelty. And beſides all this, a ſteddy and diſcreet Execution of the Laws againſt Diſſenters, might happily have been a much more mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Conduct even in reſpect of them, than the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or connivance that tempted them to preſumptuous ſins.</p>
            <p>The Diſſenters have been very induſtrious to let us know, that this is the true ſtate of the Caſe between the Government and them: That this Conſtitution ſtands no longer, when they have ſtrength and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to deſtroy it: Many of them are under an Oath
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101227:3"/>to endeavour the ſubverſion of this Church under the name of a Reformation, and could never be brought to renounce that Conſpiracy: And therefore what can be expected from thoſe that now maintain the Lawfulneſs of that Covenant, but that they ſhould conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound in Conſcience to execute their Vow, as ſoon as they could recover thoſe Circumſtances in which they took it? But the Diſſenters, you'l ſay, are divided upon this point: It is true, they are in that part that concerns their own Eſtabliſhment, but they are unanimous in Vowing our Deſtruction; and it would be but poor comfort to a Town that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to make a timely Defence, to ſee the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours that were United in the Aſſault, afterwards to fall out at the dividing of the Plunder.</p>
            <p>Nor can we be ſuſpected to ſurmiſe groundleſs and imaginary dangers from the growth of a Party that has devoted us to Ruin, and that beſides, by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and fortunate Rebellion, by the deliberate and ſolemn Murder of a moſt Excellent and Merciful Prince, by a heavy and tedious Tyranny of many years, by ſeveral Conſpiracies ſince the Reſtauration, by Aſſociation againſt the Succeſſion of His Majeſty, and a formed Project of Rebellion, which I am afraid is not yet wholly diſconcerted; and in ſhort, by the Inceſſant working of a Turbulant Spirit, have given us much greater demonſtrations of our danger, than we could have wiſhed; and he that pretends not to be convinced by all this, to apprehend danger to the Government, from the Toleration of ſuch men, muſt ſurely be deſirous of thoſe Events we apprehend, and wiſh the things which we fear.</p>
            <p>Toleration therefore can ſerve to no other purpoſe, than to be the Nurſe of a Faction that is implacable,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101227:4"/>which as it grows up, will more and more deſpiſe this Infant Diſpenſation, and contend for maſtery: Nor can we expect that they ſhould acquieſce here, when they have got ſtrength to attempt farther, no more than that a gang of ſturdy Beggars will compound for a ſmall Alms, when they have a fair opportunity to Rob. The Advocates for Toleration reply, That it is not Faction, but Conſcience which they plead for: But it is an eaſier matter to diſtinguiſh, than it is to ſeparate thoſe two things. Experience has found them to be inſeparable Companions in the body of our Diſſenters. The mind of man can make a thouſand abſtractions that are impracticable in the world; and a Philoſopher may diſtinguiſh between the Leaven, and the Maſs infected by it, and yet be never able to part them.</p>
            <p>But when one Diſſenter pleads for Toleration in the behalf of all the reſt, it is not Conſcience, but Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he would recommend; for the Diſſenters differ as much in matters of Conſcience among themſelves, as they do from us, and therefore cannot be judged to recommend thoſe Errours and Practices for Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which they themſelves judge ſinful and dam nable, upon the account of Conſcience; nor did thoſe of them that were in Power think it either law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or fit to permit all the reſt. What Spiritual Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, I pray, has a Presbyterian with a Quaker? or an Independant with a <hi>Muggletonian?</hi> or an Anabaptiſt with any of the reſt? But though they make diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Sects in Religion, yet they make but one Faction. This is the Center wherein they all unite: At an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or a Riot they make but one Congregation, and never fail to go one way; or if you would view them in greater Order, call to mind the Cavalcade that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the E. of <hi>Shaftesbury,</hi> in his ſetting out towards
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101227:4"/>the Parliament of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and you will eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the ſole Union of all Sects, and the certain Conſequence of a General Toleration. A great man indeed may ſerve his Intereſt, or his Ambition, by taking all ſorts of Sects into his Protection; but how to reconcile ſo many Contradictions of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to his own, I muſt confeſs my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too narrow to comprehend. But I muſt beg of my Reader to underſtand this, without any reflection upon the Noble Perſon that has lately ſpoke ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably of Toleration; for all that have the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be acquainted with his Perſon, or but with his Reputation, muſt do him that Juſtice, as to acquit him of all high and dangerous Deſigns.</p>
            <p>They that plead for an Indefinite <hi>Teleration to all Diſſenters whatever, upon the account of Religion,</hi> do not ſeem to me to have conſidered all the ſorts and variety of theſe to whom it is to be extended, for upon thoſe Terms the Indian Pagans may come and demand conveniences for their Pagods, and the Mahometans may pray that their Moſques may ſland among our Churches. Some fanciful man may fall in love with the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi> Superſlitions, and require by vertue of a General Indulgence, that the Ancient Rites of thoſe People may be reſtored, as well as their Languages and Learning. In ſhort, there is no Superſtition ſo ſenſleſs, or ſo barbarous, but has good Title to Toleration, <hi>if all Diſſenters whatever upon the account of Religion,</hi> are to be included. Nay, it ſtops not here, for thoſe that have no Religion at all, diſſent from us upon <hi>the account of Religion;</hi> and if an Atheiſt ſhould judge it an act of great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Generoſity, and ſurpaſſing all the Heroick Atchievements of <hi>Hercules,</hi> to attempt to redeem
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101227:5"/>Mankind from that Captivity of mind into which Religion had brought them, and from ſuch Opinions of a God as ſeem'd to him not only unmanly and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, but extremely inconvenient and oppreſſive, why ſhould he be reſtrained, if Toleration be extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to all that diſſent upon the account of Religion? And beſides, an Atheiſt can pretend Conſcience too, ſince that is nothing elſe but Human Reaſon employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the account of Religion.</p>
            <p>It may be the Council for Toleration will ſay, That theſe Atheiſts and Pagans have not retained them, and that they plead only for Diſſenting Chriſtians, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for <hi>Jews,</hi> who Worſhip the true God as well as we, though they receive not all the diſtinctions of the Deity, which Chriſt has revealed to us. Be it ſo then, ſince they may narrow their favour as they pleaſe, yet, that which I ſay, is nevertheleſs true, that the <hi>Topicks</hi> they uſe to perſuade a Toleration, will ſerve the turn of Atheiſm or Idolatry, as well as of Chriſtian or Jewiſh Diſſenters; as we ſhall obſerve when we come to examine them. And if ſuch an Univerſal To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration as we have been ſpeaking of, be not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly abſurd, that will be ſo too that comprehends all Chriſtian Diſſenters; for there have been, and may be Sects of Chriſtians ſo called, that all reaſonable men would judge more intolerable than <hi>Pagans.</hi> And that we may not fetch inſtances ſo far as <hi>Irenoeus</hi> or <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi> there are among us ſome Sects no leſs extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, than the wildeſt of the old Hereticks. The Revelations of <hi>Muggleton</hi> and <hi>Reeve,</hi> the expectation of the preſent <hi>Milinary</hi>'s. The Spirit of the <hi>Quakers</hi> are not only abſurd to the higheſt degree, but very dangerous to the Goverment, and of deſparate conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; if the infection ſhould ſpread far among the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101227:5"/>what a World were we like to have! Should <hi>Mug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton</hi> ſtrike the minds of a great number with a dread of his Commiſſion, that <hi>whoſoever he ſhall Curſe ſhall be Curſed?</hi> And conſidering there is no cheat ſo groſs, that does not take with ſome of the Common People, one would think that it ſhould be as much the Duty of the Magiſtrate, to forbid Impoſtors and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers in Religion, as it is to prohibit Juglers and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune tellers, who do not only cheat the People of their Money, but infect them with hurtful Superſtitions, to which they are of themſelves but too much inclin'd. Some Chriſtians have writ in defence of <hi>Polygamy,</hi> and affirmed that practice to be not only lawful and expedient, but to many neceſſary in point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. What if a man ſhould perſwade himſelf that he were of that number, and take as many Wives as any of the Patriarchs, it is part of his Religion, why ſhould he be proſecuted upon that account, if all ſorts of Chriſtians have right to Toleration? A <hi>Quaker</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to pay Tithes, as much upon Principle of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as he refuſes to go to Church, and to pay any civil reſpect. The firſt part concerns the Laity as well as the Clergy to look after, and to conſider how far Indulgence is neceſſary to a Chriſtian Sectary miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to the prejudice of his Neighbour; if he be ſued, or diſtrain'd, or impriſon'd, alas it is all upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Religion; take the poor man into the Verge of Chriſtian Toleration. Nay, if his Conſcience ſhould forbid him to pay Rent, he is a poor deluded man, why ſhould he be Perſecuted or Moleſted upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Religion? It will be ſaid perhaps, that no man intends to allow any pretence of Religion, to the prejudice of Common Right, for that were to tolerate injuſtice, and why ſhould I be judged in my Civil Right
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101227:6"/>by another mans Conſcience? Well, I am glad that To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration has any bounds, and that in any caſe, the Law is allowed to reſtrain a wild and extravagant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. But why it ſhould be upon this only account, and no other, I do not ſee, if juſtice will not permit that one mans Religion ſhould not do wrong to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon. How ſhall Charity permit that a man ſhould do hurt to himſelf, it is as much Charity to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain as to ſet at liberty, to tye ſome mens hands as to looſe the Chains of others; and beſides, ſince theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the underſtanding are commonly infectious, like ſome of thoſe of the Body, it is Charity to all ſuch as are capable of the infection, to uſe all poſſible means to keep it from coming to them, or of thruſting it ſelf into places of Concourſe. Since therefore there muſt be bounds put to the Toleration of Chriſtian Sects, and the Author of the conſiderations excludes <hi>falſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to Religion and Chriſtianity, thoſe wicked Enemies of Magiſtracy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. Ded. to the D. of B.</note> 
               <hi>the Sacred Ordinance of God:</hi> And in another place we have this Act of Univerſal Toleration extended <hi>to all,</hi> but with this reſtriction, <hi>as far as they are tolerable.</hi> He might have done more Service to all pretenders, if he had ſtated the caſe how far, and wherein every Sect was tolerable. It is a hard task to impoſe upon a Parliament, to examine every principle or practice of every Sect, and to ſeparate the tolerable from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable. The Presbyterians have declar'd all the other Sects to be intolerable; the Independants will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Anabaptiſts or Quakers where they have any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; the <hi>Scotch</hi> Covenanters declare againſt all thoſe that are without the Covenant; the Anabaptiſts and Quakers exclaim againſt Presbyterians and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants as intolerable, <hi>pereunt per mutua vulnera Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101227:6"/>Since therefore the conſiderer was not pleas'd to direct either the Parliament, or any body elſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern between thoſe Sects that are tolerable, and thoſe that are not, and between what is tolerable in every particular Sect, and what is not, I ſhall leave this point as needing farther explication. And I have ſome kind of ſuſpition, that he will hardly think it advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable to be very particular in diſtinguiſhing, for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things that may be to him intolerable, may be the chiefeſt delights of the ſeveral Sects, and if they are not tolerated in theſe, they would not much care whether they had any Toleration at all; what thanks will the Sectaries pay him for being tolerated by halves, to have one part of their Conſcience free, and the other bound up. And they will think themſelves no more enlarg'd by ſuch a limited favour, than a man that has but one Foot at liberty, while the other is faſt in the Stocks. In the mean time, I will take the liberty to examine certain <hi>Queries and Conſiderations,</hi> which havebeen made lately in the behalf of a general Toleration.</p>
            <p>All theſe I conceive may be reduc'd to theſe three Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Either to Religion, which they pretend enjoins forbearance, and forbids all conſtraint in Religious matters.</item>
               <item>2. Or to Reaſon, that condemns all Compulſion as unſeemly and abſurd.</item>
               <item>3. Or to civil prudence, that inclines to Toleration, as conducing much to the peace and benefit of Society.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101227:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. Quer. Upon the firſt Head, a Noble Perſon demands, <hi>Whether there be any thing more directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Doctrine and Practice of Jeſus Chriſt, than to uſe any kind of force upon men in matters of Religion, and conſequently, whether all thoſe that Practice it, let them be of what Church or Sect they pleaſe, ought not juſtly to be called Antichriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a poor man might be ſo bold with ſo great an Author, as to pretend to underſtand any thing he affects to be ignorant of, I would anſwer directly to ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement a queſtion, and affirm, that I knew ſeveral things <hi>more directly oppoſite to the Doctrine and Practice of Chriſt, than to uſe force in matters of Religion.</hi> For Example, Irreligion, Atheiſm, Blaſphemy, Burleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quing of the Scripture, Murder, Adultery, Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, Licentiouſneſs. Theſe we are ſure are direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to the Doctrine and Practice of Chriſt. But as for uſing of force in matters of Religion, I do not know any paſſage in all the Goſpels, that abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely and expreſly forbid it. Where does Chriſt forbid a Chriſtian Magiſtrate to ſilence Impoſters, Blaſphemers, turbulent Perſons pretending Religion? Where does he condemn a Religious Prince that makes uſe of his Authority, to preſerve the Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine uncorrupted, by reſtraining thoſe that miſtake dangerouſly themſelves, and would ſeduce others into the ſame errors? If any ſuch place there be, I'm ſure it is not in my Copy of the Goſpels, and I have the leſs reaſon to ſuſpect it of any fault, becauſe there is no ſuch thing in the <hi>Geneva</hi> Bible, at leaſtwiſe it could not be found, when <hi>Servetus</hi> was put to death for Blaſphe my. Nor could any ſuch paſſage be in the <hi>Datch</hi> Text or Annotations, when the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrants
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101227:7"/>were forced to travel or go to Jaol. Nor is it likely, the <hi>Lutherans</hi> would be ſo fierce, if they could have ſpy'd any ſuch paſſage as this in their Books. The vulgar Latin I need not mention, to be ſure, there is no ſuch Doctrine there, nor can it be, ſince it is ſo directly oppoſite to the Holy Inquiſition, it would be too confident a Criticiſm to adventure to give an account how this difference happens, and what Book it ſhould be that his Grace has miſtaken for the Bible.</p>
            <p>But are there not ſeveral paſſages of Scripture alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this purpoſe? there are indeed ſome, but very ſore againſt their own ſenſe and inclination, and when they are urg'd, they will have a ſpeedy an ſwer.</p>
            <p>However, is not this uſing of force contrary <hi>to the Practice of Chriſt?</hi> To none that I know: Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed did never uſe any force: No more did he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Woman taken in Adultery, nor ſentence <hi>Peter</hi> to the Pillory for denying him by a falſe Oath. Can therefore no Magiſtrate uſe any force, nor puniſh theſe Crimes without forfeiting his Chriſtianity? Our Saviour, to prevent ſuch conſequences as might be draw n from his Practice, declar'd himſelf to be but a private Perſon in all civil reſpects, his Kingdom was not of this World, he was no Magiſtrate, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did uſe no force upon any account, and therefore his example in this caſe can be no direction to him that is inveſted with civil power, and ſuſtains a Perſon quite different from the Character our Saviour bore. It is true indeed that Chriſt rebuked <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> for demanding his order or permiſſion to command
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101227:8"/>Fire from Heaven to conſume the <hi>Samaritans</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to receive him, and what could be more unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable or barbarous then this Propoſal? Why ſhould they deſire the ſudden deſtruction of Men, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver whoſe lives they had no power? and for a fault that no Law made capital? Nay, Chriſt himſelf as man, had no power to take away their Lives, tho' they had deſerv'd it; nor can we be ſure that this which ſo much provokes their indignation, was any matter of Religion at all, but only a refuſal of a Civil and Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Reception to our Saviour on his Journey towards <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but whether he preach'd there or no, or that they did any affront to his Character and his Doctrine, the Scripture doth not ſay, and the contrary is moſt probable from the Relation of the Evangeliſt, but neither this, or any other inſtance of our Saviours Practice, obliges the Conſcience of the Civil Magiſtrate, not to puniſh ſuch Perſons or Sects of Chriſtians that corrupt the Religion, and diſturb the quiet of the Church or State under his charge, ſince therefore the Practice of puniſhing Diſſenters is contrary neither to the Doctrine, nor Practice of Chriſt; I hope they that uſe it upon great occaſions, may be diſcharg'd of the odious imputation of Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>all thoſe that Practice,</hi> this odious method, to uſe <hi>forcible means in matters of Religion, what Church or Sect ſoever they may be of, are Antichriſtian.</hi> What ſhall we do for Chriſtians? The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this rate muſt be the moſt Antichriſtian of all. The Presbyterians were always as much Antichriſtian as they were able, and the Independants of <hi>New-England</hi> are as viſibly Antichriſtian, as if they had all the Horns and Marks of the Beaſt; and if theſe be all Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101227:8"/>who have we left capable of the benefit of To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration? For ſurely if any ſort of Men be intolerable, they are ſuch who truly deſerve that Title.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſideration</hi> 1. Another Author ſtirr'd up by <hi>the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent diſcourſe of the D. of B.</hi> enlarges upon this Head, and ſhews, <q>that the Apoſtles were only commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd to Preach and Teach the Chriſtian Doctrine, that they were Embaſſadors to beſeech Men to be reconcil'd to God, and not to uſe any forcible means to bring People to conform to his Worſhip.</q>
            </p>
            <p>An Author after all his pains, may ſurely be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd to give his Book what Title he pleaſes, provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Reader may have his Freedom to Interpret. This Book is made up of ſeveral parcels, which he calls <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> and if this firſt muſt paſs under that Title, it cannot be in the literal ſenſe, but ſhould be interpreted as Dreams are by contraries. For if our Author had conſidered, tho' never ſo little, he muſt needs have diſcerned that all this is no more againſt all forcible means, than it is againſt humane Learning; the Apoſtles uſed as little of one as of the other in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of the World; let us allow then that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles us'd no forcible means to convert the World, but reduced it only by perſwaſion, what then? Then no body elſe ought to think themſelves wiſer than the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and to endeavour to convert the World by force; agreed: But what is all this to our preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? Then no forcible means ought to be us'd to bring Diſſenters to Church, or to hinder their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Here the conſideration is too ſhort, and draw it as long as you pleaſe, will never come to the point, unleſs he can ſatisfy us in this one thing, that there
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101227:9"/>may be no other Methods us'd in the Government of a Church already Eſtabliſh'd, than thoſe that have been us'd in the Converſion of Infidels; this whole matter will perhaps be much clearer to him, if he pleaſe to take notice of theſe plain and certain Truths.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Apoſtles had, and us'd greater Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over thoſe they had already converted, than over thoſe that were yet to be converted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That tho' they were ſent onely as Ambaſſadors to unbelievers, to perſwade them to be reconcil'd to God, yet when they had effected that Reconciliation, they were, by vertue of the Commiſſion, the Rulers and Governours of thoſe new Conqueſts of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That tho' their Commiſſion gave them no civil Authority, yet were they impower'd to uſe forcible means in matters of Religion, and to reduce thoſe to Conformity, that walk'd diſorderly, and departed from the form of wholeſom Doctrine delivered to them: For I take Diſcipline to be ſomewhat different from <hi>perſuaſion;</hi> and the Rod that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of how Metaphorical ſoever it be, to be ſomewhat more than <hi>beſeeching.</hi> In ſhort, thoſe that reſiſted their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, felt the weight of it. Some were delivered to Satan, to learn not to Blaſpheme, becauſe they had made <hi>Shipwrack of the Faith.</hi> They were caſt out of the Society of Chriſtians, not only from all corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence in matters of Religion, but alſo from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of civil Society and good Neighbourhood; and therefore ſuppoſing any one whole City or Province then of the Chriſtian Religion, the Excommunication of an Apoſtle would have had the ſame force with a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101227:9"/>civil Out-lawry or Baniſhment, and how can you think him not baniſht to all effect, with whom no Perſon of his Country will have any communication? And what would have become of <hi>Cerinthus</hi> in a Chriſtian City, where St. <hi>John</hi> had been Biſhop, if all would have been of the ſme mind with the Apoſtle, (as probably they had) not to come under the ſame roof with that Blaſphemous Heretick.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Deſtruction of the fleſh, that the Spirit might be ſaved;</hi> though I dare not be poſitive in the expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, does without diſpute ſignify ſomething of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible means, and of a different nature from perſwaſion, and the vehement expreſſion of St. <hi>Paul</hi> concerning the Turbulent people that diſturb'd the Churches of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia; I wiſh they were cut off that trouble you,</hi> is of a ſtrein beyond beſeeching. I ſhall not inſiſt upon theſe paſſages, leſt I ſhould be thought to plead for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, and to juſtify the putting of men to death for Religion, which I am as far from approving, as I am from a deſire that I might be the firſt ſufferer by ſuch a Law; for I look upon all Capital puniſhments not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too ſevere for the miſtakes of the underſtanding, though there might be ſome wilfulneſs and perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs mix'd with them, but of all ſorts the moſt impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and abſurd, ſince he that takes away the Life of a Heretick, commits an inviſible cruelty greater than that which is ſeen, by taking from him at the ſame time all opportunity of returning to a better mind; and ſince all forcible means us'd in matters of Religion, ought to be directed to the benefit of thoſe toward whom they are us'd, as well as the ſafety of others, nothing can be more contrary to, or deſtructive of that end, than the putting of men to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101227:10"/>death for errors of belief, how groſs or dangerous ſoever they may be. And this practice is the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, becauſe there are other means ſufficient to prevent the ſpreading of the diſeaſe, and may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute not a little to the cure of the infected.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, if the Apoſtles, who had no Civil Power, did yet puniſh their Diſſenters, not only by ſharp reproofs, but with Civil inconveniences too, ſurely the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, who is endu'd with that power from above, may ſo far make uſe of it, upon the account of Religion, as to ſecure the Peace of the Church, and Purity of the Chriſtian Doctrine, as to render men of corrupt and turbulent minds uneaſy in the outward circumſtances of Life, and to tye up their hands from diſperſing the miſchief among the People: And laſtly, to diſcourage wanton, or perverſe, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning perſons to attempt upon the Faith and Charity by which his Subjects are united.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſid.</hi> 2. To the ſame Head we may reduce the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Conſideration: <hi>That the uſing of outward Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in matters of Religion, does only ſerve to make men Hypocrites, but works no ſaving Converſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That compulſion in matters of Religion may make ſome Hypocrites, muſt be allow'd, ſo do all Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, Laws, ſenſe of ſhame, and the Opinion of the World; and if nothing that may ſerve to make a Man a Hyprocrite may be us'd, we muſt lay aſide not only all Penal Laws, but all Charity too: But that this Compulſion ſhould <hi>ſerve only</hi> to make men Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, dropt I am afraid from our Author without conſideration, for there may be ſome that reſure to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101227:10"/>conform to the eſtabliſh'd Worſhip, becauſe they are aſham'd to depart from what they have once profeſs'd; they dread the reproach of their Party, and the gaze of a Congregation upon a new Convert. There may be others that refuſe to conform, as much upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Intereſt as of Conſcience; for who does not know that the Diſſenters are more engag'd by their mutual dealing among themſelves, than they are by their Church Covenant; for a poor Presbyterian or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant to go to Church, is to forfeit all his Cuſtom, and to be beggar'd, and to fall under a ſecret Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that will more certainly undo him, than the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of all the Penal Laws; therefore to theſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion ſerves not to make them Hypocrites, but to free their Conſcience from the practice of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, that was in ſome meaſure become neceſſary to them, and cannot be eſteem'd the forcing of Religion, but the breaking of an unlawful and dangerous combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and ſince there may be Hypocrites of both ſides, why ſhould they be angry if we take away their chaff, which may make their heap ſhew bigger, but add little to the value of it: Such as may do them no great Spiritual good, but may do the Government a great temporal miſchief. Laſtly, ſince according to the Doctrine of moſt of the Diſſenters, he that is a real Saint, cannot by all the force in the World be made a Hypocrite, why ſhould they be afraid that compulſion will effect impoſſibilities? And if thoſe upon whom it can have any influence were Hypocrites before, I do not ſee any reaſon why they ſhould be ſo much concern'd for them.</p>
            <p>Experience has taught us that compulſion in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, ſerves many times to render men
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101227:11"/>more teachable, and willing to be inſtructed; when a man has brought himſelf into inconvenience, he is deſirous to examine what it is for, and when he has weigh'd the Reaſons on both ſides, he may be of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that his duty and his intereſt go the ſame way. How many Diſſenters keep off they know not why? how many rail at our Service that never read a word of it? That diſparage our Miniſters, and never heard them? How difficult is it to obtain from the Zeal of many Diſſenters ſo much Truce, as to hear what one can ſay to them with patience and civility, but this frowardneſs is ſomewhat abated, when they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves entang led with difficulties, and then they may condeſcend to liſten to reaſon; &amp; this opportunity may be ſo well improved, that in concluſion they ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this compulſion, as a ſingular Mercy of God, and apply the words of the Pſalmiſt to their Caſe, <hi>Before I was troubl'd I went wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now ſuppoſe the worſt, that this compulſion would ſerve to make many Hypocrites, and that moſt of them at firſt might come to Church only to ſave their Purſes, yet they may not continue always ſo, but it is probable they may profit ſo much by what they hear and ſee, as to be convinced of the folly of their former way, and what they did at firſt upon mean and ſordid reaſons, they may afterward continue to do out of conſcience and choice; ſo God is pleaſed ſometimes graciouſly to take the wiſe in their own Craftineſs. Some have gone to Church only out of curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and have been caught; ſome have gone to mock, and return'd in Tears; <hi>Saul</hi> went to the Prophet only to enquire of his Fathers Aſſes, and received an Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which he little expected, and ſince truth and right
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101227:11"/>are as manifeſtly on the ſide of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the Laws, why, ſhould not we hope well, if by any means Diſſenters may be brought but to the hearing of the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind.</hi> This Text of Scripture, with which he is pleas'd to tip the end of this Conſideration, is brought thither much againſt its natural inclination, and I ſhould think that they who ſo much abhor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion in matters of Religion, ought not to uſe ſuch open violence to the Scriptures, to force them to their purpoſe, for thoſe Expreſſions relate only to the chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and forward manner of the Miniſters doing their Duty, and have not the leaſt hint about compelling of Men to come to Church.</p>
            <p>To the ſame Head we muſt reduce the third Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <p>Conſid. 3. <hi>All ſorts of Perſons are for Liberty of Conſcience for themſelves, even thoſe that are moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing upon others. They would count it hard meaſure to be conſtrained to perform or forbear ſuch and ſuch things, which concern their Religion, or to ſuffer unpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable penalties; And why ſhould not the Church-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants make the Presbyterians, the Independants, the Papiſts oaſe their own in this point, ſeeing they are all fellow Chriſtians? Therefore whatſoever things ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do ye ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Rule which is the Foundation of all Juſtice and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101227:12"/>Charity, would be the Ruin of them both, if it were not reſtrained to things equally lawful or reaſonable: Now if it be an indifferent matter, what Religion or Sect any man is of, it will be very unreaſonable not to allow as well as to deſire Toleration. But it will be ſtill an abſurdity in him that believes all Religions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to deſire any Toleration for himſelf, ſince his principle may comply with any ſort. But thoſe that deſire Toleration are of another mind, they think themſelves in the Right, and all thoſe with whom they refuſe to join in the wrong; and for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that they which be tolerated themſelves, they refuſe to Tolerate others, with a <hi>non-obſtante</hi> to our Saviours Rule. If ſome Religions are falſe, if many Sects are in their very conſtitution and eſtabliſhment ſinful, this Rule cannot reach the preſent caſe. What Criminal can be puniſh'd, if for the Reading of that Text, he muſt have the benefit of his Clergy? What Child may not emancipate himſelf from diſcipline, if it will ſerve his turn to ſay to a Maſter or a Father, would you be us'd ſo your ſelf? There are ſome differences in Religion, about matters of the higheſt importance; there are Opinions of ſeveral Sects, that are Blaſphemous: There are others that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and eſſerate Humane Nature, inſtead of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving it. There are other miſtakes of leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence in Religion, but from ſeveral Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of greater danger to the Government, all which if they have any claim to Toleration by this Rule, of doing to others as you will be done by, have no better than that which with the ſame Juſtice, may be made by all the deadly ſins.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>why ſhould not the Church of</hi> England, <hi>make the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101227:12"/>Presbyterians Independants, and Papiſts caſe her own in this caſe, ſeeing they are all Fellow Chriſtians?</hi> Nay, why not the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Quakers, Muggletonians,</hi> (for they claim kindred too, when it is low with them; and then we are all Brethren and Fellow Chriſtians,) and if there be any other Sect unnamed, ſuppoſe it included, and then one Anſwer may ſerve them all, ſo that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> cannot make their caſe her own. 1. Becauſe ſhe thinks there is a great deal of difference, for many of them hold falſe and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Opinions, and practice things utterly unlawful, and unchriſtian. 2. She ought ſo to judge ſince there is a real difference between Truth and Falſhood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Good and Evil, between thoſe things in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, whether they are lawful or unlawful. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ſhe be in poſſeſſion of the Truth, ſhe ought no more to make theſe Diſſenters caſe her own, than a Judge ought to make that of a Priſoner at the Bar, whom he knows to be guilty, to be his own; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if he were himſelf in the ſame circumſtances of guilt, Fleſh and Blood would tempt him to deſire to eſcape; he ought not to determine therefore the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal before him muſt not ſuffer.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If this be all, they that diſſent from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may judge as hardly of her as ſhe does of them; confeſs'd, </q>but who can help all this? yet the nature of things is not chang'd, by their thinking one way or other, in the ſame debate, many differing Parties may be very confident, and but one in the right, and be too certain that he was ſo, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the contradiction of all the reſt: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I do not ſee of what great uſe the hard opinion of the pretenders to Toleration concerning the Church
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101227:13"/>of <hi>England,</hi> can be to them to obtain it; one would think while they are Candidates for favour, this might be better omitted.</p>
            <p>I am afraid that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independants</hi> will owe them but little thanks for tacking the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that Abominable Antichriſtian name, upon their Plea for Toleration, for ſurely the Aſſociation cannot yet be ſo far worn out, nor the Cabaliſtical deviſe <hi>of no 'Popery no Slavery,</hi> be utterly forgot; ſurely their Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Commiſſion to extirpate Antichriſt and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, is not yet given up: If they can endure this, they are much degenerated from their firſt principle of heat; nay, they muſt have chang'd their very ſpecies, and it will puzzle <hi>Malibranche</hi> with all his Ideas, to define a Proteſtant Diſſenter, when his Zeal againſt Popery is laid aſide.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Arguments offer'd at this time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend a general Toleration, from the nature and the precepts of Chriſtian Religion, and let any body judge after all the odious repreſentation of Compulſion in matters of Religion, whether from all that is ſaid, it does appear, that a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, whatever his own perſuaſion be, is bound in conſcience to allow every one the Exerciſe of his own way, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his own Opinion, how Abſurd, how Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, how Damnable ſoever it may be; for this is the juſt Paraphraſe of univerſal Toleration.</p>
            <p>And now for my part, to ſhew how little I am given to contradiction, I am content to yield the queſtion to the Conſiderer, or to the Noble Perſon, who is above conſideration, if their Principles will be ſatisfy'd with theſe Arguments alledg'd on their behalf,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101227:13"/>let the Conſiderator then go back (for I will not be ſo abſurd as to ſend a Perſon of Quality upon ſuch an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand) and conſult thoſe whom he nominates for Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the <hi>Presbyterians, Independants,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and if they declare it for their Opinion, <hi>that it is the Will of God,</hi> that neither Reſtraint nor Compulſion ſhould be us'd to Men in Religious Matters, let them obtain all the Indulgence they can wiſh; but as to the laſt of theſe, I ſhall not need to trouble them or my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, becauſe I cannot tell how well they may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted; for if a man may gueſs at his correſpondence, he ſeems to hold more with the Proteſtant Diſſenters: Nor is it needful to make long enquiry in a matter ſo well known. The Judgment of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> concerning this point is as clear, and as viſible, as the Fire with which they uſe to reduce Hereticks to Aſhes.</p>
            <p>It muſt be confeſs'd, that ſome Princes of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, partly for reaſons of State, and partly out of the Clemency and Generoſity of their temper, have ſhielded their Proteſtant Subjects from the fury of the Eccleſiaſticks, and abhorr'd to be the Executioners of their Hypocritical cruelty, who pretend, that they have no power themſelves to take away Life; ſo the High Prieſt and the <hi>Jews</hi> declar'd it was not lawful for them to put any man to death, yet forced <hi>Pilate</hi> to paſs Sentence upon the Son of God, becauſe they had before judged him worthy of death.</p>
            <p>Among thoſe barbarous Pagans, where men were us'd to be Sacrificed to Idols, the Butchery was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways accounted part of the Prieſts Office, and I ſee no reaſon why the <hi>Dominicans</hi> or the <hi>Grand Vicar,</hi> if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101227:14"/>they will have the Blood of Hereticks, ſhould not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the Odium, and the pollution of ſhedding it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. I know ſome Princes have paid dear for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to deſtroy ſuch as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> called He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, one was murdered by a <hi>Dominican,</hi> a Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Inquiſition by his Vow, and another ſtabb'd into the Heart by a Diſciple of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> whether be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſuſpected ſome Favours or Indulgence for Hereſie might remain there, or becauſe they were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient to wait longer for that noble part, which that great Prince promiſed them a Legacy after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe.</p>
            <p>Since then our Conſiderer can have no hopes of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving his conſideration to this Party, and to bring them to a vow with him, that it is not the Will of God, that any force ſhould be us'd in matters of Religion; Let him go to the Presbyterians, and enquire what is their opinion concerning Toleration; it is true, they have not been always in the ſame mind concerning this Goſpel Duty; before the late Rebellion, when they were in their Infancy, they were as tender-hearted as one could wiſh, but when they had once prevail'd, and got the power into their hands, they began to limit, and to diſtinguiſh, and at laſt openly to deny the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that, which the Conſiderer makes to be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible a Chriſtian Duty; nay they could not in Conſcience conſent to a Toleration, even of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in Arms, thoſe that fought in the ſame Cauſe, and approach'd neareſt to their Principles; all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that could be us'd were not able to reconcile the conſcience of a Presbyterian to a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Independants, the Debates are Printed,<note place="margin">The Grand Debate.</note> and will furniſh any one that will take the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101227:14"/>pains to look into them, with the Arguments then us'd on both ſides of this Queſtion.</p>
            <p>The <hi>London</hi> Miniſters of that time, for fear the Aſſembly might be carryed away by importunity, or diſpute, to yield any indulgence to their Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Brethren, ſent them their Objections againſt it, in a Letter dated <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. 1645. In which they declare, that <hi>To get a warrant to authoriſe their Separation from, and to have a liberty of drawing members out of it, i. e.</hi> Their Church, <hi>This we think to be plainly unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Independancy is a Schiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Now we judge that no Schiſm is to be tolerated in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some of the Independants in their Books have openly avow'd, that they plead for Liberty of Conſcience for others, as well as for themſelves.</hi> To plead for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Toleration was then, it ſeems, argument enough not to indulge the pleaders even in their own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular way.</p>
            <p>Now could they in Conſcience have allowed their diſſenting Brethren any Indulgence, they could not have refus'd perſons that had deſerv'd ſo well of them; but it was a thing of ſuch a nature, they muſt not by any means yield to. For <hi>hereby</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we ſhall be involved in the guilt of other mens ſins, and thereby indanger'd to receive their plagues.</hi> After this the Ordinance which the Independants ſtyled the Bloudy one, was drawn up, which made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral miſtakes in Religion, to be felony, without bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101227:15"/>of Clergy. Others to be confuted by a hot Iron, to be apply'd to the face of the Blaſphemer. Others to be puniſh'd by impriſonment; for example, <hi>to ſay that the Government of the Church by Presbyters,</hi> ſuch as it was then projected <hi>was <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſuch an inſolence, that impriſonment ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rather an Indulgence than a puniſhment. This Ordinance was read twice in the Houſe of Commons, and ſtiffly debated, but the Sectaries and <hi>Eraſtians</hi> uniting their Forces againſt the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Presbytery, that had projected alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the ſuppreſſion of all the reſt, this was hindred from paſſing into an Act, but it was nevertheleſs defended and juſtify'd by the Presbyterian Party up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions; and tho' they could never diſpute it into a Law, yet ſometime after they paſs'd ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordinance, by which they Condemned ſeveral erroneous Opinions, and Blaſphemies; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared ſome to be Capital, but this was much ſhort of that which we have been ſpeaking of; however that Toleration which they were not able to confute by a Law, they were more zealous to oppoſe by their writings, and by all other means they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd uſeful to that purpoſe. They appointed Days of Humiliation for the Hereſies they could not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh by the Sword, and employ'd the moſt Zealous and Eloquent of their Party, to repreſent the ſin and miſchief of. Toleration, and to inflame the minds of men againſt thoſe Errours and Sects, which they had been hitherto hindred from extirpating. There was no man of that Time that wrote more fully againſt Toleration than <hi>Edwards,</hi> who in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe againſt Toleration, which he intitles, <hi>The caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101227:15"/>down of the laſt and ſtrongeſt Hold of Satan,</hi> makes Liberty of Conſcience ſuch an Abomination, that the High Commiſſion, and the greateſt Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Biſhops were rather to be indur'd: And I know not how Toleration can have the impudence to lift up its head after that in this Book <hi>it is clearly prov'd and demonſtrated by Scripture, ſound Reaſon, Fathers, Schoolmen, Caſuits, Proteſtants, Divines, Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>To be utterly unlawful and miſchievous,</hi> and this, <hi>both of an univerſal Toleration of all Religions and Conſciences, and of a limited and bounded, of ſome Sects onely,</hi> how, <hi>clearly this is prov'd or demonſtrated by him,</hi> I am not at preſent much concern'd to ſhew, having mention'd this Author with others of his Party only to eaſe our Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and to direct him in his enquiry, concerning the Judgment of the Presbyterians about the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Toleration, in which it is deſir'd they may have their part, and ſince they have declar'd againſt it, it is a ſort of Compulſion and Perſecution, to put it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them whether they will or no.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay to all this? <hi>Was the Doctrine and Practice of Chriſt</hi> then known? Was not <hi>the will of God</hi> revealed <hi>againſt all forcible means in matters of Religion?</hi> Was it not obſerv'd, <hi>that Compulſion ſerv'd only to make men Hypocrites?</hi> Was not this Rule, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you,</hi> &amp;c. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into the Canon in thoſe days? The Scriptures ſurely are the ſame, and if they were then ſo clearly againſt all Toleration, they muſt be ſo ſtill; and have we heard of any New Revelation ſince, concerning this matter? So that we may aſſure our ſelves, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101227:16"/>the Presbyterians will depart from what they have once aſſerted with ſo much noiſe and confidence of Demonſtration. Yet ſurely our Conſiderer could never have been guilty of ſuch unacceptable officiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without ſome probable preſumption of their good liking, for whom it was intended. Nor can we imagine any man ſo fool-hardy, as to hazard the diſgrace of being diſowned by thoſe, for whom he ſo earneſtly intercedes. Admit then the mind of the Presbyterian Diſſenters be chang'd, and that their preſent Judgment is more moderate, and that their Advocate produce it under their hands, it will do them but little ſervice, becauſe thoſe that are not their Friends, will look upon the Inclination they may now have for Toleration, to proceed rather from their outward condition, than any inward conviction of mind; for in contrary Declarations of the ſame Perſon, that is commonly judged to be moſt ſincere, and according to his mind, that is made when he is in full Liberty, whereas the Act of a man under any reſtraint or neceſſity, is ever accounted leſs valid, and a leſs certain Declaration of his mind.</p>
            <p>The Independants, who offer'd the Presbyterians ſo many Scriptures and Reaſons for Toleration, and took it hainouſly to be rejected by their Brethren, whom they knew to be but Uſurpers of Authority, after they themſelves had taſted of the forbidden fruit of Power, their Eyes were open'd, to diſcern plainly as many reaſons to refuſe Indulgence in Religion, as ever they had offer'd for it when their condition was lower. In the year 1650. there was an Act made
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101227:16"/>againſt Blaſphemous and dangerous Errors, and the <hi>Inſtrument of Government,</hi> which <hi>Cromwel</hi> publiſh'd afterward, did not only exclude Prelacy and Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from all benefit of Toleration, but made it Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to maintain ſeveral Opinions in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: By vertue of theſe new Laws, <hi>Muggleton</hi> and <hi>Reeve</hi> were condemned to <hi>Bridewel, Naylor</hi> was Stigmatiz'd, <hi>Biddle</hi> the <hi>Socinian</hi> was Try'd for his Life, for denying Chriſt to be the Son of God, and eſcap'd not ſo much by the Clemency of thoſe that Ruled then, as by an Error in his Indictment; it was in vain for any of theſe to plead their Conſcience, or that they were proſecuted againſt the Will of God, and the Rule of Common Juſtice, the Ruling and the Arm'd Conſcience, would ſtill aſſert its Power and Dominion over the Conſciences of Inferior Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>
               <q>It may be ſaid, that this ſeverity was us'd only againſt groſs and intolerable Opinions, to prevent their ſpreading among the People.</q> Well; If this Reaſon be good for them, why not for the preſent Government, eſpecially ſince the Right and Title of it, is ſomewhat clearer than that of the Independant Dominion? That the Opinions then puniſhed were Groſs, and Blaſphemous, alters not the caſe, ſince they were part of the belief, and the Religion of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Perſons or Sects; and if no forcible means at all ought to be us'd to reduce Mens Conſciences, how come theſe to be excepted?</p>
            <p>
               <q>However you will ſay for them, that they us'd no forcible means to make Men Conform againſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101227:17"/>their Judgment to their way of Worſhip:</q> There is a certain Author, who ſtiles himſelf <hi>a Friend to true Reformation, and whoſe Teſtimony we have no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſuſpect, that aſſures us of the contrary from the Practice of thoſe times.</hi> [A Lamentable Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the effects of Toleration. By <hi>V.T.</hi> 1656.] This zealous Perſon, to let the Magiſtrate underſtand, <hi>that providing Able, Pious Miniſters, is not all they can do,</hi> tells this ſtory, that a Godly Citizen of <hi>London;</hi> 
               <q>took to his Apprentice a prophane Country Lad, (ſome Cavalier-bred Boy belike) and having ſent him to Church once or twice, <hi>to hear a Soul Searching Miniſter,</hi>
               </q> (Pardon my Authors Phraſe.) <hi>Alas poor Boy, his Hear was oppoſite to ſuch holy mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as Praying and Preaching, ſo he would come no more there, but the Maſter thought he had not done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but did command and compel him conſtantly to hear that Miniſter, as he thought it was his Duty,</hi> ſo at laſt the Boy was Converted, then he concludes; <hi>What Chriſtian can or will blame this Maſter?</hi> The ſame Author proceeds further to inform us of the Godly Practice of thoſe times. <hi>The Officers of the Army</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>in their Garriſons,</hi> (<hi>I am ſure in</hi> Jamiſes) <hi>do compel their Souldiers to hear the Publick Sermons, all, except ſome Anabaptiſts.—How ſmartly have I ſeen the Souldiers caned unto the Sermon in</hi> Weſtminſter Abby? <hi>It is a good Example for all in Authority, from the greateſt Prince and Parliament, to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Maſter or Parent,</hi> it was time now to object, <hi>this is againſt Liberty of Conſcience, no ſuch matter</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies our Author,) <hi>it is againſt the liberty of being as bad as men will, but not againſt the Liberty of being as good as men will, if neither Anabaptiſt, Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101227:17"/>nor Independant Miniſter will not ſerve them, their Conſcience is not tender in any ſenſe but ſear'd:</hi> A wonderful Liberty of Conſcience, a delicious varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, this is ſufficient to pleaſe the moſt Nice and Faſtidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Palate. And this brings into my mind ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther odd choice offer'd to <hi>David,</hi> either to endure ſeven years Famine, or three Months flight before his Enemies, or three days Peſtilence.</p>
            <p>Yet after all this, the Independants in <hi>England,</hi> when they were at their greateſt height, being but few compared to the bulk of the Nation, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing only in the Army, and that too by conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with other Sectaries, we cannot certainly judge how far they approv'd of Toleration in their hearts. They ſpoke indulgently and moderately of ſeveral Sects, whoſe aſſiſtance they were forc'd to court, and joined with them in a common Defence againſt Presbytery, but there was no alliance at all of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but only of intereſt between them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as their intereſt varied, ſo did their Judgment ſecin to do concerning tolerating other Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>In <hi>New England,</hi> where the Independants Reign, and prevail as well by their number as Authority, the caſe is very much altered, between them and the other Sectaries, there they prohibit all other Religions and Churches but their own, <hi>i. e.</hi> there ſhall be no Preaching, no Congregation, no publick Worſhip, but after their way, and of their own approbation. So that an Anabaptiſt, or a Quaker is more at eaſe here, under the moſt active proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101227:18"/>of this Government, than in <hi>New England,</hi> that was once accounted the refuge of the ſcrupulous, But that all men may know how Toleration thrives in that Country, I will mention the Heads of ſome of their Laws concerning Eccleſiaſtical Matters.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <q>
                     <hi>No Church to be gather'd without</hi> the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Magiſtrate dwelling next, and of the Elders of the neighbouring Churches.</q>
               </item>
               <item>2. <q>No perſon to Preach publickly and conſtantly to any people,</q> either in Church ſociety or not, where any two Organick Churches, Council of ſtate, or General Court ſhall declare their diſſatisfaction thereat, either in reference to doctrine or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</item>
               <item>3. <q>Eevery one that Renounces his Church eſtate, ſhall forfeit to the Treaſury forty Shillings a month, ſo long as he ſhall continue in that his obſtinacy.</q>
               </item>
               <item>4. <q>Every one muſt come to Church upon the Lords day, days of Humiliation and Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, or for every default to forfeit five Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</q>
               </item>
               <item>5. <q>The Obſervation of <hi>Chriſmaſs</hi> Day, to be puniſh'd with a mulckt of five Shillings.</q>
               </item>
               <item>6. Hereſy to be puniſhed by Baniſhment or Death, and many diſputable points determin'd to be Hereſy.</item>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:101227:18"/>
               <item>7. Whoſoever ſhall be found to have any of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleton,</hi> or <hi>Reeves</hi> Books, ſhall pay ten pounds, he that Harbours a Quaker ſhall pay forty Shillings an hour, he that ſhall go to their meeting ſhall pay ten Shillings, and the Speaker five pounds.</item>
               <item>8. A Quaker is to be baniſhed, and if he return, to be whipp'd out of the Country at a Carts tail, and ſtigmatiz'd, and if he come back a ſecond time, to be put to Death.</item>
               <item>9. Anabaptiſts are made incapable of dwelling there by their Law concerning Hereſies, which declar'd it to be one to deny the lawfulneſs of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Baptiſm.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I am almoſt afraid that ſome who have not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the difference between a ruling Independant and an Independant under hatches, will be apt to ſuſpect I do them wrong in theſe Citations, but if any be ſo ſcrupulous of believing theſe ſummary excerptions, he may without much difficulty, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ſatisfy himſelf by looking in the Body of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, that they have printed, which will inform him more at large, what liberty of Conſcience is practis'd in New <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe are ſcare-crow Laws ſurely, and never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be put in Execution. Alas the complaints of New <hi>England</hi> Perſecution, has made ſo much noiſe this many years, that the whole World has rung with it. R. <hi>Williams</hi> made no little ſtir about
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101227:19"/>
               <hi>Cottons</hi> Bloudy Tenet, and the barbarous uſage he and ſeveral other Diſſenters from the Churches eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd there, had met with. The Caſe of the <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toniſts</hi> has been publiſh'd, and it was thought very hard meaſure, that when the Eſtabliſh'd Sect had driven theſe out of their Dominion, to ſeek Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Liberty under ſome of the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Indians,</hi> their Perſecutors purſued them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by force of Arms diſſodged them from this Refuge. I need not multiply Inſtances of this kind, all ſorts of Diſſenters there drank of the ſame Cup, and made the ſame Complaints.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps may be deſirous to know how the Independants of <hi>New England</hi> can defend themſelves againſt the Arguments of their own Brethren here for Toleration, when they come to be us'd by the Sectaries that diſſent from their Rule; Such as they are put upon us for Demonſtrations, and thought by our Diſſenters unanſwerable; therefore it may not be a miſs to give a brief account how the diſpute runs there, and in what manner the Proſecutors vindicate themſelves againſt the importunate ſaucy Pleas which the Diſſenters there do continually make for Liberty of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For one Proteſtant Congregation to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mathers Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to <hi>St Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lards</hi> Biſhop againſt the <hi>Anab.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>is more unreaſonable,</hi> (ſays the Anabaptiſt Apology) <hi>than all the Cruelty of the Roman Church, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Mather,</hi> ſays <hi>No: For Proteſtants puniſh,</hi> tho not perſecute <hi>Proteſtants; nay, as the caſe may be circumſtanc'd, even a Congregation of ſuch
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101227:19"/>as call themſelves Proteſtants,</hi> if he had added <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants</hi> too, the Antitheſis had been ſomewhat more bold, and more viſible: This he proves by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Puritans, from whom theſe Churches pretend to be deſcended; and precious Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> their Apoſtle, who is bold to denounce, <hi>That if the Magiſtrates of</hi> England, <hi>would tolerate Tranſgreſſours of the Rule of Godlineſs, God would not long tolerate them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In</hi> England <hi>(ſay the Anabaptiſts) the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants are our Advocates for Toleration, in New</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>they perſecute us themſelves. p.</hi> 16. <q>And the Writers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> lay hold of this occaſion to expoſe their inconſiſtence with themſelves;</q> 
               <hi>Mather</hi> mumbles this Objection, but is not able to take it off: It is <hi>not for their Opinion, but for receiving perſons excommunicated by the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Congregation,</hi> that they are puniſhed, but this fault they are as guilty of in Old <hi>England,</hi> as in New <hi>England. Then he cannot be perſwaded that any Independants would deſire indulgence for ſuch Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts as theirs.</hi> Yet there can be no difference ſhewn between thoſe that are taken here into protection, and thoſe that are perſecuted there. Whence then can proceed ſo different an uſage of the ſame ſort of men? Alas the myſtery is not very deep, and may be reſolved into a Common Rule of Humane Wiſdom very well known, that it is no matter how liberal a man is at the expence of another; but he ought to be more wary, when he is to give out of his own ſtock.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:101227:20"/>
            <p>The Anabaptiſts complain, <hi>That it is againſt the deſign of the firſt Planters, that left</hi> England <hi>and went thither for Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> to lay any reſtraint upon it.<note place="margin">Animadverſions on the N. E. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabapt. p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Willard</hi> anſwers without mincing, <hi>That their buſineſs was not Toleration, but to ſettle and ſecure Religion to poſterity, according to that way which they believed was of God.</hi> p. 11. <hi>The Magiſtrates there were Chriſtians, and held it their duty to maintain and ſtrengthen Chriſtian Religion by Civil Laws. All Reformers have done ſo, and the Church ever ſince the Apoſtles.</hi> Poor diſſenting Conſcience, where canſt thou find Reception, if theſe Colonies of Diſſenters ſhut the doors againſt thee?</p>
            <p>The Anabaptiſt cry's, <hi>it is againſt their Brethren. p.</hi> 9. The Independant is not ſatisfy'd that they are ſo near of kin, and though they were. <hi>Yet Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline rightly adminiſtred, is not againſt Chriſtian Charity, the want of it does rather argue want of Love,</hi> Lev. 19.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is the part of the men of this World to perſecute,</hi> (ſays the Anabap.) yet ſometimes (replies the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant) <hi>it proceeds from Godly Zeal againſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gentle means will prevail moſt according to the Diſſenters judgment. <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>But experience tells the Independant that ſuch a Rough thing as a</hi> New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>Anabaptiſt is not to be handled over-tenderly. The Spirit which they have alwaies diſcovered under the greateſt diſadvantages, eaſily tells us, what they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101227:20"/>would have been, if circumſtanced as thoſe whom they accuſe.</hi> And Laſtly, that they might not be miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, they declare the proper Subject of their juriſdiction. <hi>We do not pretend to a Lordſhip over Conſcience, yet the outward man is Subject to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now he that can reconcile theſe Laws, this practice, this Doctrine of the Independants, to the <hi>Conſideration</hi> for Toleration, may make a match between Antipathies, and a friendſhip between con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions; nay, may reconcile the Conſcience of a Scotch Covenanter, to that ſhort prayer for which he holds a ſingular deteſtation, <hi>i. e.</hi> God ſave the King, <hi>idem jungat vulpes &amp; mulgeat Hercos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Anabaptiſts, Quakers, Socinians,</hi> and other Sects, becauſe they are not particularly mentioned, I cannot tell how far they may be concern'd in this Plea for a general Toleration, or whether they will be judg'd tolerable or no, and therefore it will not be neceſſary to ſay any thing concerning them. And ſince theſe have not yet had the fortune to be upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in any of our Revolutions, we cannot conclude with any certainty, whether they would continue as zealous for Indulgence as now they are: It being difficult now to diſcern whether their importunity for Toleration proceeds from the Inward Man, or only from their outward Circumſtances. When they had got ſome power in <hi>Cromwels</hi> Army, they began to be ſomewhat turbulent, and addicted to Level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which imply'd a very fore impoſition upon the Conſciences of Rich Men, and thoſe that were
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101227:21"/>in Authority. But in thoſe Countries where the Anabaptiſts prevailed upon their firſt appearing, they left ſuch inſtances of Blood-ſhed and Devaſtation, as the ſtory of no Chriſtian Sect can parallel.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Quakers,</hi> how their Spirit would determine concerning Toleration, if they were in power, is as hard to foretel, as it would be to ſhow, what courſe, or frolick a mad man would take, that were broke looſe from his Keeper. But if all <hi>Bedlam</hi> ſhould break looſe, and make themſelves the Maſters, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it would be neceſſary to have recourſe to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Stratagems, and that a man would be in no little danger, that would preſume to continue in the Exerciſe of his own Wits.</p>
            <p>Having ſhewn what Conſcience, they that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from us, make of Indulging their Diſſenters, and that none are more vehement againſt. Toleration when they are in place, than thoſe that are now ſo importunate for it, we may conclude that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all they alledge from Scripture, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſtian Religion, to make us believe that we ought in Conſcience to indulge Diſſenters, they are of our ſide, and do not believe any thing of what they ſay, for it is unconceivable how they can reckon that our Duty, which would not be ſo to them plac'd in our circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Now if neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles have ever enjoin'd a general Toleration of all Chriſtian Sects, and the Diſſenters, when uppermoſt, declare this
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101227:21"/>to be true: The Chriſtian Magiſtrate is ſomething more at large, and has greater liberty and ſcope to judge of the Reaſons and Conſequences of allowing or refuſing it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Topick from which the D. of B. and the Conſiderer argue againſt all Compulſion in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, is the abſurdity and unreaſonableneſs of the thing: Therefore the D. puts the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Topick. <hi>Whether there can be any thing more unmanly, more barbarous or more ridiculous, than to go about to convince a mans judgment by any thing but Reaſon, it is ſo ridiculous, that Boys at School are whipp'd for it, who inſtead of anſwering an Argument with Reaſon, are Loggerheads enough to go to Cuffs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this reaſoning be good, the Maſter that Whips is the veryeſt Loggerhead of all: Has whipping any demonſtration in it to convince the judgment of Boys? The Maſter therefore ſhould convince thoſe Blockheads by a grave diſcourſe, as a certain Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Perſon of great moderation, is ſaid to have done upon the like occaſion, ſaying, That it was the higheſt abſurdity in Metaphyſicks for Intellectual or Rational Entities to fall out: Ay, this is convincing, and as certainly parts a fray, as a little duſt ſtops the fury of Bees in the very heat of Battel; for Gods ſake tell me, you ſevere Aſſerters of <hi>Priſcian,</hi> what Rods and Ferula's do in your Schools? What are theſe Twiggs of the Tree of Knowledge, or theſe, are they Chips of any Oracular Oak? What can
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101227:22"/>thoſe things contribute to the enlightning of the underſtanding? Look to your ſelves, for the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of humane Reaſon and Liberty, will call you to account, for making uſe of thoſe Enſigns of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and Inſtruments of Perſecution; for it is barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to go about to convince one's underſtanding, which is true or falſe Latin by any thing but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; it is ridiculous to imagine that whipping ſhould correct a weak or a miſtaking judgment.</p>
            <p>But Boys are perverſe and wilful, and will not be perſuaded to their Duty by Reaſon, therefore Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline muſt be us'd, not to convince their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but to mend their temper, and to bring them to a Teachable Diſpoſition; be it ſo: Now if Men may be ſometimes Children in the temper of their minds, as well as in underſtanding, what ſhall be done? If they are Perverſe, Sullen, Raſh, Wanton, to ſay nothing of Malice, Intereſt, Deſign, which are more than childiſh faults, is there no remedy but downright Reaſon? And yet theſe Indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will not permit the party affected, to hearken to, or to conſider, or comply with Reaſon, but when theſe Obſtructions are remov'd, reaſon may have its effect, and finiſh the Conviction.</p>
            <p>Yet ſtill, <hi>to go about to convince a mans judgment by any thing but Reaſon, is unmanly,</hi> &amp;c. It is certainly ſo. And an unmannerly Fellow might ſay, that if his Grace means to convince any mans judgment, by this Quere of the reaſonableneſs of Toleration, he may be in danger of falling under his own Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But to the Queſtion, I do not believe we ever
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101227:22"/>had a Parliament ſo unlearned, as to take Penal Laws for Demonſtrations, or to think that any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can immediately convince the underſtanding. Penalties in matters of Religion are deſigned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ſuch evil obſtructions as lie in the Paſſage to a mans right Reaſon, that it may judge more equally and impartially of that which is laid before it. Every mans reaſon is not to be ſpoken with at all times, there may be Prejudice, Wilfulneſs, or Intereſt, that like ſo many ſurly Door-keepers, forbid all acceſs to right reaſon; they will ſay perhaps, my Lord is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed, or he is in Company, or entertains him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a private Friend, or is a ſleep, and muſt not be moleſted; ſo an ordinary Perſon muſt depart, tho' his buſineſs be never ſo reaſonable; but if an Officer from the King ſhall demand Audience, all excuſes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, the Doors fly open to the Authority, that would not ſtir before the Juſtice of the ſame Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and the great Perſon ſo difficult to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd, muſt then hearken to, and comply with Reaſon; if therefore the Penalties which cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the judgment, may yet reſcue it from the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſs, and teachleſneſs it had contracted, and from that Slavery in to which the will and paſſions its own natural Subjects had reduc'd it, and reſtore it to the liberty of conſidering the Reaſons laid before it; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſonable man I hope will be ready to diſcharge them of the infamous Titles given them in this Quere.</p>
            <p>Conſ. 4 <hi>The good Rules of Humanity and Common Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, are openly violated by uſing of Force in Matters of Conſcience. Men do abhor to thruſt that Meat or
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101227:23"/>Drink down their Neighbours Throat, that will not agree with their Stomachs; they ſay commonly pray take what likes you, why are they not ſo civil in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, have compaſſion one on another, be Pitiful, be Courteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it were as indifferent a matter, what Religion or Sect one ſhould be of, as whether he ſhould eat Beef or Mutton, I muſt confeſs it would be very unhoſpitable to oblige a man to any one more than another. But I have not heard before of this new mode of Civility, pray take what God or Religion you pleaſe, I will not preſcribe to you, be of what Sect you pleaſe. Yet if in this variety there ſhould be any thing that you knew to be unwholſom or mortal, it would be but a ſorry civility not to forbid him to touch it, or not to ſnatch it forcibly out of his hands. Or if by miſtake one ſhould eat Hemlock, and declare he did not love Oyl, it could not ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be accounted ſo very Rude and Barbarous, to pour ſome down his throat. But it goes againſt their ſtomachs: So does many Medicines that have good effect. The Phyſicians muſt not uſe Aloes, or Rhubarb, becauſe they make one ſick forſooth, in the way to health, but the Chymiſt and the Quack<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cry, be kind to nature; Let your Medicines be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and eaſy. Indulgence is the only way to heal: After all this, what ſhall we ſay to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Text of Scripture. <hi>Have compaſſion one of another,</hi> &amp;c. Is it not a very tender compaſſion, ſo to ſuffer a man to go on undiſturb'd in damnable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour? Is it not a moſt obliging Courteſy, to ſuffer a man to dye, rather than uſe ſo much rudeneſs as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101227:23"/>to pull him by the Noſe? St. <hi>Jude</hi> has left us ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of direction, he bids us to make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and to ſnatch ſome out of the fire, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Conſiderers courteſy, we muſt have a care of being too rough with them, leſt while we ſnatch them out of the fire, we ſhould happen to hurt them, or put out an Arm.</p>
            <p>Conſi 5. <hi>The Church Proteſtants in</hi> England <hi>have been diſtreſſed by hot doings heretofore in the Reign of Queen</hi> Mary, <hi>when they were accounted Criminals for not conforming to that Worſhip which was then the eſtabliſhed Worſhip of the Kingdom. And they ſhould have taken heed before now, of what they did, and of what Spirit they be ſtill of in perſecuting others, ſince they know not how ſoon that part of the Wheel which has been, or is on the ground, may come to be at top, and fall the heavier on them upon this account; for with the ſame meaſure men mete withal, it ſhall be meted to them again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ever I underſtood the juſt reproach of a <hi>Trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> it is ſomething of kin to this Argument, it is the name, as I take it, of one that dares not be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and do his duty for fear of Conſequences. What if the Parliament ſhould be angry? What if there ſhould be a Court Revolution? What if the Faction ſhould get the better? So he floats, and rowls, and recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, as this or that apprehenſion prevails: How politick this conſideration may be, does not much concern me, let the Author abound in his own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and diſtant projects of ſelf preſervation, the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101227:24"/>preſent Queſtion is, What is fit and ought to be done, and not what will come of it; and beſides the iſſue of this conſideration is very uncertain, for there may be Inconveniences in the way of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, as well as in that of ſeverity. If you provoke a Party, the Wheel may turn round, and they have their turn of being uppermoſt, and then will be in a capacity of revenging themſelves. If you tolerate and give way to Diſſenters, you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to their Growth, and with your own hands help the Wheel to turn round, and when they are got to the Top, they may forget all your former connivances. There is no end of purſuing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of things that have ſuch variety of chance, and are influenced by every little incident; the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way ſurely is for a man to be uniform to himſelf to do his duty, and leave the ſucceſs to God: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how ſeaſonable it may be put people in mind at this time of Queen <hi>Marys</hi> daies. Thoſe that can aquieſce in the faith and juſtice of a King, who has been alwaies ſo faithful a Subject to his own word, can no more apprehend <hi>the hot doings</hi> of thoſe times would return, than that the time it ſelf ſo long paſs'd ſhould be recall'd: But there are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences as full of fears and jealouſies of perſecution for, as they are of ſcruples in their Religion, and condemn themſelves never to be ſatisfy'd. This is not very ſtrange, for it is natural for every man to hope and fear according as he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>I wonder our Author ſhould give himſelf the trouble to go ſo far back as Queen <hi>Marys</hi> Reign,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101227:24"/>to humble the <hi>Church Proteſtants,</hi> with a proſpect of their ſufferings, he might have found a Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no leſs calamitous to them, and of a more freſh and ſmarting Remembrance; I mean the <hi>Reign of the Diſſenters.</hi> The <hi>Church Proteſtants</hi> are ſenſible enough, that they are mortal, and have had their turns of ſuffering as well as others. But it is ſomewhat an odd way of moving for Indulgence, to commemorate the inſolence or cruelty, which thoſe that pretend to favour, have heretofore us'd towards the Church that is eſtabliſh'd by Law, and it ſounds like a threat to ſuggeſt, you know what you have ſuffered, therefore, <hi>take heed how you proſecute others.</hi> Who are theſe others? Diſſenters? Why ſhould the intimation of Queen <hi>Marys</hi> days, make us take ſuch heed of that? If thoſe times ſhould return, it is not likely that the Proſecution of Diſſenters, would be laid to our charge as Hereſy, or <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> The Diſſenters of all men living, have the leaſt reaſon to reproach us with proſecuting theſe, ſince they were the conſtant Inſtigators of the Magiſtrate to execute the Laws made againſt the Papiſts, and upon all occaſions expoſed the <hi>Church-Proteſtants,</hi> as Popiſhly affected, becauſe they did not always proſecute that Party with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt rigour: But if our danger cannot prevail with us to take heed of proſecuting, yet ſurely our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours admonition muſt: <hi>With what meaſure you mete, it ſhall be meaſured to you again.</hi> If the meaſure be juſt and reaſonable, why ſhould we fear that the ſame ſhould be returned; If the return be not juſt, then it is not the ſame meaſure. The Judges had need to underſtand this place better than our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderer, otherwiſe they would have but a ſorry
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101227:25"/>defence to make if the Criminals they had puniſh'd, ſhould come to make reprizals, and to judge them by this Text, according to the intent of this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſi. 6. <hi>Conformiſts and Non-Conformiſts, do all agree in the ſubſtance of Chriſtianity, in the ſame Articles of Faith, in the ſame Rule of Manners, in the Apoſtles Creed, and the ten Commandments. There is one Body, one Spirit, one Lord, one Fleſh, one Baptiſme. As a variety of flowers may grow on one Bank, ſo may Proteſtants and Papiſts live in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c. <hi>There is much more reaſon to love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the many things wherein we agree, than to fall out for thoſe wherein we differ, and though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have Communion in the ſame external Worſhip, we can, and have Commuuion in the ſame internal Adoration of the ſame Bleſſed Trinity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Wolf ſhall lye down with the Lamb,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is an intolerable iniquity, to uſe different and deceitful weights, one ſort to buy, and another to ſell by. It is the ſame ſort of cheat, to repreſent things of more or leſs moment, not as they are in themſelves, but only according to the occaſion we have to make uſe of them. When Diſſenters ſpeak of Toleration, then we agree all in the main, the differences are only about ſmall matters, and why ſhould not we indulge ſomething to leſſer miſtakes? But if you deſire them to take this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument back by the ſame weight, and tell them, that ſince we agree in the main, why ſhould they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101227:25"/>be ſo unreaſonable as to ſeparate from us, and to make or continue a perpetual breach for things of little moment? then they preſently change their note, and every difference is of the higheſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>i. e.</hi> Whatſoever they would have us to grant, is but a ſlight matter; But for them to yield any of thoſe little things, is as much, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Faith, or to Sacrifice to an Idol.</p>
            <p>Now let us obſerve the truth and conſequence of what is offer'd in this <hi>Conſideration, all do agree as to the ſubſtance of Chriſtianity, and in the ſame Articles.</hi> In what ſubſtance? In what Articles? In all? This is too much, for we have ſome difference I think with the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks about the infallibility of their Church, the Supremacy of the Pope, the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and theſe they take <hi>to be Articles of Faith, and of the ſubſtance of Religion;</hi> and we judge to be miſtakes very abſurd, and of long and dangerous conſequences; <hi>But we have the ſame Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles Creed;</hi> So we have the ſame Scripture, yet if they lay yet broader Foundations, and build upon it what Faith they pleaſe, how ſhall theſe their Creed or Scripture ever determine any difference about thoſe Additional Articles, or what Plea is it for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, that we agree in many points, but that we differ in other of great importance; as if an Argument concerning the obligation of nine of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhould be a reaſon to permit the obſervation of the tenth to diſcretion, and that we ſhould rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the many Commandments about which we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, than one or two, perhaps ſhort ones, which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101227:26"/>ſome tender Conſciences might deſire to be indulg'd. The <hi>Socinians</hi> and we differ about the Perſon of Chriſt, and the Merit of his death, about the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity, and many things more of leſs moment; but theſe things ſurely were ever accounted of the ſubſtance of Chriſtianity, and yet they make a difference between us and the <hi>Socinians:</hi> The <hi>Quakers</hi> who reſolve all their Faith into the Authority of their Spirit, and revile the Scripture, and deny it to be the Word of God, do not agree with us ſo much as in the Foundation of Religion; theſe two err dangerouſly concerning the Trinity and the Incarnation of the Son of God, and I am afraid our Author did not conſider theſe Sects, when he tells us; <hi>That we can, and have Communion in the ſame Internal Adoration of the ſame Bleſſed Trinity.</hi> I cannot tell to what purpoſe our Author brings into this conſideration a paſſage of Scripture about Unity, where he pleads for the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Diviſion; <hi>There is one Body, one Spirit, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm.</hi> Since ſeveral of the Diſſenters have neither the ſame <hi>Faith,</hi> nor <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> much leſs the ſame Body or Spirit; The Anabaptiſts look upon our Baptiſm as void; The <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> for the moſt part, uſe no Baptiſm at all: Now I would fain underſtand by what figure of Speech, theſe may be ſaid to have the ſame Baptiſm with us? Well; admit there be ſome things of moment, about which we differ, yet the number of thoſe is greateſt about which we are agreed, therefore, <hi>there is much more reaſon to love one another, for the many things wherein we agree, than for to fall out for thoſe wherein we differ.</hi> Whether we ought to love one another for thoſe things in which we agree, is not the queſtion; for it is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:101227:26"/>certain we ought to love one another, whether we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in many things or few, but the point in diſpute is whether this love obliges us to permit thoſe that differ from us, to Confirm themſelves in thoſe errors, which are the occaſion of our difference, by having them Preach'd and Argu'd, and Maintain'd in their Aſſemblies; Is it an Act of Chriſtian Charity, to ſuffer <hi>Quakers</hi> to enjoy all opportunities of being confirm'd in their madneſs, and of ſeducing ſilly people? If we love the Perſon of a <hi>Socinian,</hi> muſt we therefore give him leave to propagate his Doctrine, and to teach men to deny their Lord that bought them? becauſe we have Charity for <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> ought we therefore to Tolerate them to Re-baptize thoſe they have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to believe themſelves no Chriſtians, or the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants,</hi> becauſe our Faith is not much different from theirs? ſhall they out of pure love be licens'd to gather Select Congregations, to draw away as many as they can from the Church, to oblige them by a Vow as Solemn as that of Baptiſm, not to return thither, nor to forſake their new Fraternity?</p>
            <p>Theſe are the things which we would gladly have the Diſſenters forbear, and uſe all lawful means to hinder them, not becauſe we have no love for them, but out of pure compaſſion, becauſe theſe things they are ſo deſirous to be indulg'd in, would do them and others hurt, and this is all the quarrel we have with them, this is the falling out with which our Author is offended.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay now to the <hi>Mahomitan</hi> Parable? <hi>That variety of Flowers may grow on the ſame Bank.</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:101227:27"/>It is certainly more agreeable to the Principles of him that ſpoke it, than thoſe of a Chriſtian, for the <hi>Turks</hi> permit <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to live among them, and to enjoy the Exerciſe of their Religion, becauſe they think both of them may be ſav'd by vertue of that Religion they reſpectively profeſs. But our Church paſſes a very ſevere Cenſure upon thoſe that ſhall ſay, that every man may be ſav'd by that Law or Sect which he profeſſes. But what if theſe Flowers prove Weeds, and grow too faſt, what if they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy, and hurt the reſt, what if they are like Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>de Luce</hi> ill Neighbours according to the Old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, what then? They muſt certainly in prudence be a little diſcouraged and kept under, or by ſome good Art be brought to change their deſtructive and unſortable nature.</p>
            <p>In what manner this Prophecy of the Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Diſſenting Natures, <hi>The Wolf ſhall lye down with the Lamb, and the Leopard with the Kid,</hi> is to be accompliſh'd, I am not well aſſur'd, however I have ſome reaſon to ſuſpect, that it is not to be done by the way of an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Toleration, becauſe this deſcription ſhews not only, that they ſhall not hurt one the other, but that they ſhall be of one Fellowſhip and Communion; they ſhall feed and lye down toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; whereas Toleration ſeems to do no more than to ſhut up theſe ſeveral Creatures in diſtinct apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the ſame Grate; but if you would know when a Presbyterian, or Independant, or Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, will not hurt, I can tell, without the Spirit of Prophecy, it is then only when they have no power to do hurt.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:101227:27"/>
            <p>Conſ. 7. <hi>The</hi> French <hi>Proteſtants, who are Diſſenters from the Eſtabliſh'd Government of that Kingdom, are kindly receiv'd and ſuccour'd by</hi> England, <hi>and when the</hi> French <hi>King is highly blam'd by</hi> Engliſh <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and perhaps too by ſome</hi> Engliſh <hi>Catholicks, for Perſecuting his peaceable Subjects, ſhall we do the ſame thing in our Kingdom, which we condemn in another? Therefore thou art inexcuſable O Man that judgeſt, for thou that judgeſt another, doeſt the ſame thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not enquire what <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants do highly blame or condemn the Actions of the <hi>French</hi> King; thoſe of my acquaintance are not very forward to cenſure and condemn Princes, nor can it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that whoſoever is kind to a Stranger forc'd out of his Countrey, does preſently engage himſelf in the whole Merit of his Cauſe. But as for the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, we conceive our compaſſion to be the more due to them, becauſe they ſuffer for a Religion, which we verily believe to be true, which we are not able to ſay of ſeveral of thoſe that plead for Toleration. In the next place, they were peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and had not provok'd their Prince by any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious or Turbulent Behaviour, in the Minority of this King, when the diſcontents of <hi>France</hi> were very high, and the Authority of the Government low. They behav'd themſelves ſo well as to deſerve his publick acknowledgment, which I believe our Diſſenters are too modeſt to pretend to; for if they ſhould; yet there is hardly any body ſo ignorant of their proceedings, but can juſtly reproach them
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101227:28"/>with having laid hold on every advantage of publick diſtreſs, to weaken firſt, then to deſtroy the Government: They never fail'd to join themſelves with every Faction againſt the Crown, and ſtill brought a form'd Faction to every diſcontented great Man, and offer'd themſelves ready inſtruments of his Ambition or Revenge. But we have yet farther cauſe to Commiſerate the ſufferings of the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, becauſe they tell us, and we have no reaſon to disbelieve them, that they were inflicted without Proceſs or Form of Law, and directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt particular Rights and Priviledges granted to them by former Kings.</p>
            <p>For their Churches had been long ago taken into the protection of the Government, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd by Laws. Special Judicatures were erected in their favour, where the one half were of their Religion, and ſeveral other Priviledges granted them, to ſecure their perſons and eſtates from Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and the malice of their Enemies; and how they have forfeited all, I do not know. But our Proteſtant Diſſenters were never own'd by our Laws, nor men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in them, but as a factious and ſeditious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that was by all due means to be ſuppreſs'd. There never was any agreement or accomodation between the Government and them; for while they could hold their arms in their hands, they would never hearken to any, and therefore it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if we have ſo many Laws againſt Diſſenters, to forbid Conventicles, to oblige them to come to Church; ſince this Government thought they could never take too great ſecurity, from a Party
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101227:28"/>they had found to be implacable. <hi>Therefore thou art inexcuſable O man,</hi> whoever thou art, that wouldſt ſtir up the Reader, nay recommend to the Parliament for a Parellel Caſe with ours, one that has ſo little reſemblance with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Top.</hi> 3. We are come now to the third and laſt Topick of the Advocates for Toleration, and that is the benefit and advantage of the Kingdom, by Improvement of Trade, to which Indulgence is eſteem'd to be ſo ſingular a Nurſe, that it cannot poſſibly thrive or ſubſiſt without it. Wherefore the D. of B. makes this Quere, <hi>Whether the practice of it, i. e.</hi> of uſing any compulſion or reſtraint towards mens Conſciences, <hi>has not alwaies been ruinous and deſtructive to thoſe Countreys, where it has been us'd either in Monarchies or Common-wealths? and whether the contrary practice has not been ſuccesful in all thoſe Countreys, where it has been us'd, either in Monarchies or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have great obligation to this Noble Perſon, for waving all the advantages which a fruitful wit might have given him upon this Subject, of reaſoning without end of the poſſible or probable miſchiefs or advantages ariſing to Monarchies or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, from the granting or refuſing Toleration; and for referring this whole diſpute to the deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of experience. The Queſtion therefore cannot but have an eaſy iſſue, becauſe any man of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary underſtanding, that has read ſome Hiſtory,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101227:29"/>or made any Obſervation in the World, may be capable of deciding it. As to the firſt part- of the demand I do believe there have been, and are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdoms that have receiv'd no manner of da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, by denying a Toleration to ſeveral Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. What Calamity has befallen <hi>Denmark</hi> or <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> upon this account, where you will meet with no other Churches, but the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and if ſome Indulgence has been heretofore offered there to People of other Nations, this comes not under our Queſtion, for ſtrangers may be more ſafely tolerated than Subjects, becauſe the removal of them, when they grew trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome is more eaſy, and has not ſo bad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. But not to Travel ſo far for an exception to this General Quaere, I beleive there was no Kingdom more flouriſhing than this was under Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> I. And yet then there was as great or greater reſtraint upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as at any time ſince: The <hi>Roman</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, though a very numerous and formidable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the beginning of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> were brought to our Churches, by the ſingle force of the Act of Uniformity, which left Diſſenters to the Cenſures of the Church, and added no other puniſhment than a light mulct of a Shilling for every default. And this Uniformity that is the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Toleration, did in a few years ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh that Party, that the Pope was oblig'd to command thoſe who retain'd any reverence for his Authority, to ſeparate themſelves, and to abſtain from coming to our Churches: It would have been a ſtrange Paradox in Politicks, in thoſe daies, to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:101227:29"/>plead for the Toleration of thoſe the Government did ſo much fear. But however, this Compulſion did not prove in the leaſt <hi>ruinous,</hi> or deſtructive to this Kingdom: And when that Party fell into dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enterprizes, the Laws grew ſtill more and more ſevere, in obliging them to a conformity with the eſtabliſh'd Religion.</p>
            <p>The Puritans were as little indulg'd by that Queen, as the Papiſts, as her Laws do ſufficiently declare, and all her time by due execution of Laws; that Faction was low and inconſiderable, that the care taken then to ſuppreſs them, ſeemed to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed rather from the foreſight of ſuch troubles, as this Faction might create to ſucceeding Princes, than any apprehenſion of preſent danger. I need not mention thoſe Anabaptiſts, and wild Fanaticks, that were put to death in her time, not ſo much I conceive for matters of Religion, as crimes againſt the State, it is enough that all the World knows, that there was no Toleration in thoſe daies, and yet they were as ſerene, as proſperous, as happy, as any paſs'd over the head of this Nation, at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe during the late Uſurpation, which was the only time of Toleration in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>If we can give any credit to thoſe Obſervations, which our Republicans and Diſſenters have made of the Original of the late Confuſions, we owe them all to a pretended Toleration, or ſome ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance which they ſuſpected, and from this root they deduce all that followed; true or falſe, real
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:101227:30"/>or pretended; the Enemies of the Government made much more advantage of it, than either the Government, or thoſe for whom the favour was ſaid to be intended.</p>
            <p>I might inſtance in Monarchy's, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, that are of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that they have received no great prejudice by not granting a Toleration for all Sects of Religion; and if ſome of the moſt zealous Perſecutors of the Reformation have fallen into extraordinary decay, we may impute it to the Judgment of God upon them for reſiſting the Truth with ſo great Cruelty, and not for denying licence to every thing or Sect, that had the pretence or Cant of Religion. Beſides in thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, ſome that have inquired into the reaſons of their decay, have obſerved ſeveral other falſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, much more pernicious than the denying of Toleration.</p>
            <p>The laſt Exception I ſhall make is from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth and Kingdom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver flouriſh'd more than when there was no Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, never was in worſe Condition, than when there was; And this inſtance has ſomething more of Authority than the reſt, becauſe this People were govern'd by Gods own Laws, and ſometime more immediately by God himſelf as it were in Perſon, and yet during all the time of his Theocracy, there is not the leaſt Indulgence or Liberty of Conſcience to be found upon Record.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſo far was his Government from any ſuch thing, that he made a perpetual Decree, that if any
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101227:30"/>Perſon, or City, or Tribe, ſhould fall away from his Worſhip, and ſerve other Gods, the reſt inſtead of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging, or neglecting the errors, were to proſecute them to utter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Now, leſt it may be thought, that under Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy this might be juſt, becauſe Idolatry was a ſort of High Treaſon, but in other Governments the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ceaſes; it is plain that the ſame Law was put in Execution by the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah;</hi> who are not only commended by the inſpir'd Writers, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to have been bleſs'd with unuſual proſperity for thoſe proſecutions. I would not be thought to recommend theſe Proceedings, as Precedents to be tranſcrib'd by Chriſtian Princes, it is only upon the Queſtion of Fact, that I produce this inſtance, to ſhew there may be ſuch a thing as a proſperous King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Common Wealth, without the help of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Toleration.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond part of the Quere; <hi>Has not the contrary practice been always ſucceſsful to thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where it has been us'd, either in Monarchies or Common Wealths.</hi> I think it a hard matter to find many Kingdoms or Common Wealths, where a general Toleration has been us'd; ſome have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd one, or perhaps two ſorts of Diſſenters in Religion, but this does not anſwer the end of thoſe Queres, or of the <hi>Conſiderations, which is univerſal Toleration;</hi> but have not thoſe been moſt ſucceſsful that have tolerated moſt? This is not certain, for I think in the time of the late Uſurpation, there was a great variety of Sects permitted to uſe their ſeveral ways, but the ſucceſs, God be thanked, was ſuch as honeſt men did wiſh and pray for; they had
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101227:31"/>too great ſucceſs indeed at firſt againſt the King and the Church, but then Toleration was ſcarce begun or deſign'd; there was then but one Rule of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, the Covenant was impos'd upon all; And the Independants did for a good while diſſemble their Exceptions. But afterwards when every Sect demanded the liberty of its own way, and Religions were multiply'd beyond Computation, the Fruits of Toleration did quickly appear, every Sect as it ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd a little ſtrength from a State of Toleration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to affect Dominion, and this did quickly ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite, and rend the Body of thoſe Tyrants, that it was impoſſible for them longer to ſubſiſt, and ſo made way to that glorious Revolution, whoſe influence makes us ſtill happy and proſperous, and it makes no difference in this caſe, whether a Government be rightful or uſurp'd; the ſame method of Indulgence will have the ſame conſequence, only Uſurpers have more excuſe for allowing Toleration, becauſe it is more neceſſary for them, than for a Rightful and long Eſtabliſh'd Dominion; and therefore tho' it be a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous courſe, they muſt take it, becauſe they have no better to take.</p>
            <p>I know the Example of the United Privinces is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Recommended by our Diſſenters, and is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by the Authour of the <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it equally ſerves both their occaſions, for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth, and Toleration; however, I believe this inſtance is commonly ſwallow'd down whole with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſidering the particular reaſons or circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that may induce them to tolerate ſome Religions, which may render their caſe very different from ours. <hi>Some Religions,</hi> I ſay, becauſe they do not tolerate all, or whatever they do at this time, they have been
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101227:31"/>in the memory of man ſo far from allowing an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Toleration, that they exceeded all their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Neighbours in violence and ſeverity, againſt thoſe that diſſented from their Eſtabliſh'd Religion, tho' in matters very obſcure, and of inſuperable diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty. However, ſince this Example of the <hi>Dutch,</hi> is inſiſted upon by all the Advocates for Toleration, as an unanſwerable Argument of the benefit of that courſe, I will give a brief account of ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as determined them to Indulgence, and the ſecurity they take a gainſt all the civil conſequences of it; neither of which are to be found in our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, their Common Wealth was Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally made up of ſeveral Religions, or Sects, which are as eſſential parts of their Conſtitution, for they were not only preſerv'd by Strangers from <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> that Fought their Battels, but many out of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> fled thither as to a common refuge; and were all as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into this Common Wealth; every one of theſe Nations had their Churches not only tolerated, but Eſtabliſh'd by Authority, and paid by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments; ſo every Nation and Sect, uſe their own Forms and Languages, only the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are much degenerated, partly by their own fault, inclining to the Puritan way, and accommodating themſelves to the manner of the Country, partly by the care which the <hi>Dutch</hi> do, and have ever us'd to diſcourage Epiſcopal Miniſters, making great ſcruple of admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any one they ſuſpect to have Epiſcopal Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So Toleration was at firſt the neceſſity, not the choice of that People. But after this Eſtabliſhment,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101227:32"/>the meaſure of their Toleration being full, whoever oppos'd the Religion Eſtabliſh'd, and departed from the Rule of their Church, found but very ſorry quarter. When the <hi>Socinians</hi> appear'd firſt in thoſe Countries, the States took the Alarm, and Baniſh'd thoſe Hereticks out of all their Dominions. Then <hi>Arminius</hi> his Scholars, preſum'd to find fault with the <hi>Dutch</hi> Catechiſm, which was their Eſtabliſh'd Doctrine of their Church, and to divide Communion upon it; they were condemned by the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> and the Sentence was Executed by the Magiſtrate, with ſo great ſeverity, that all the Neighbouring Countries were fill'd with the complaint of the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Remonſtrants. The moſt Eminent and Active of whom were forced to fly their Country, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure cloſe Impriſonment at home, ſo that, tho' they had more different Religions in their firſt Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than we, yet they endeavour'd, we ſee, to keep their firſt Eſtabliſhment entire, as well as we do ours, by forcibly ſuppreſſing thoſe that aſſaulted it; nay, they us'd greater ſeverities upon this occaſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Diſſenters, than ever we have done to ours. Yet during this proſecution of Diſſenters, they had the beſt ſucceſs that ever happened to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth; before that time they ſtruggl'd for life, but now they enlarg'd their Frontiers and their Trade, and advanc'd ſo far in ſtrength and reputation, as to become the moſt powerful Common Wealth in <hi>Europe;</hi> not that their ſucceſs and proſperity is to be imputed to this Perſecution, but it ſeems by this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that forcible means in matters of Conſcience does not always ruin, nor is the good ſucceſs of a People in Trade or War always to be imputed to a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:101227:32"/>general Toleration. I do not pretend to juſtify thoſe proceedings, nor do I alledge them upon any other account, than to ſhew that <hi>Dutch</hi> Toleration, has bounds, and that they have been proſperous while they proſecuted, a very conſiderable Party, both for number and intereſt, upon the account of Religion.</p>
            <p>But beſides the difference of their firſt Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ours, there are ſeveral other circumſtances in their Government, that renders Toleration leſs dangerous to them than it is to us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Dutch</hi> Populace have no voice at all in chuſing of their Magiſtrates; there are neither May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, nor Aldermen, nor Sheriffs, nor Common Council, nor Knights and Burgeſſes for Parliament, to be Elected by their Commonalty. There are no Juries to Judge of Matter of Fact, or of Right by way of Concomitance, in any Cauſes Criminal or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. So that tho' the number of any Sect may increaſe, yet has it but very little influence upon the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſince it can have no hand in diſpoſing of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Offices; nor are the Members of it capable of any, whereas no Sect can thrive with us, but you preſently find the evil effect of it in our Parliaments, in our Juries, and conſequently in all the diſtribution of Juſtice, and eſpecially in the Government, and temper of our Corporations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the People have no part in the choice of their Magiſtrates, ſo neither can any one be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any part of their Government, who is not of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101227:33"/>the States Religion, and this to appear not by any ſingle Teſt, as once coming to Church, or Receiving of the Sacrament in order to be qualify'd, but by the courſe of their Life, ſo that if any Perſon have given any ſuſpition to that Colledge of Magiſtrates, into which he is ambitious to be received, that he is not in his Heart of their Religion, there is no more hopes of his ſucceeding, than that a Perſon ſhould be made Pope, who is under imputation of Hereſie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is ſaid, that the Government of their Cities have a more abſolute and ſummary way of Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Perſons ſuſpected of any deſign or practice, to the prejudice of the publick quiet, and thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique and ſquinting diſcourſes, and practices of Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that can ſcarce give matter to an Information with us, are there eaſily ſuppreſs'd by an admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for ſuch Perſons to depart the place.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The temper of the People is ſomething more Phlegmatick and leſs zealous than ours; the ſeveral Sects are content with following their Trade all the Week, and their Religion on <hi>Sunday,</hi> without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling their Heads with gaining <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> or adding to their numbers, whereas with us every Sectary, almoſt, is a kind of Apoſtle, and is in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, ſtill Preaching up his own way, and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing upon all thoſe with whom he has to do, and railing againſt what is uppermoſt.</p>
            <p>Now the Diſſenters who magnify beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the happineſs of the <hi>Dutch</hi> in the uſe of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Toleration, would be very loath to purchaſe it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:101227:33"/>at the ſame rate, that is, by reſigning up for that Liberty of Conſcience, all ſuch Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of Engliſhmen, whereby they are made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of giving diſturbance to the Government. I am affraid there would be many Diſſenters found upon the Tryal very unwilling for a licence to go to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles; to forbear going to Elections of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Men; and to oblige themſelves not to go to the <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> provided they be excuſed for not going to Church.</p>
            <p>Yet after all, the <hi>Dutch</hi> Toleration has one poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſadvantage, and that a heavy one, that ſeeing there are ſome Sects now tolerated, almoſt as nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as that Party of the Eſtabliſh'd Religion, ſome of theſe either by Domeſtick Tumult, or Forreign ſupport, may eſtabliſh themſelves in the place of thoſe who are now in Authority, and by putting out a ſmall number of men, now in Government, not only make themſelves Maſters of it, but main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and keep it by the number and ſtrength they have already; and which will more and more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by the Acceſſion of thoſe whoſe Religion is gain, of which ſort that Country has its ſhare. Whereas in thoſe Countries where there are indeed ſeveral Religions, if the Diſſenters are ſo kept un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as to bear no proportion to thoſe of the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though they may make a Tumult, or get the better for ſome little time by the advantage of a ſurprize, yet will they never be able to maintain themſelves, and muſt give way to the Reſtauration of the firſt Eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:101227:34"/>
            <p>The Conſiderator is very particular upon this Topick, and does not only tell us that proſecuting of Diſſenters deſtroys Trade, but inſtances in ſome Proſecutions of ſo ill conſequence, that the King and Council were forc'd to over-rule them, or elſe vaſt multitudes of Poor People, who were not any ways infected with the Opinions of Diſſenters, muſt have been undone.</p>
            <p>Conſ. 8. <hi>Proſecuting Diſſenters</hi> (he ſaies) <hi>is a great diſadvantage to the Trade of the Kingdom, they being a chief Part of the Trading People, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Liberty of Conſcience, muſt be the moſt effectual means to reſtore it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have good reaſon to believe that our Author over-reckons, when he makes the Diſſenters <hi>a chief Part of the Traders:</hi> For though they conſiſt chiefly of Trades-men, and thoſe of the ſmaller ſort, yet they are but an inconſiderable Part in reſpect of the whole. And we muſt note, that all are not Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out of Conſcience, that ſpeak favourably of their Party, or favour them in a Vote; and it is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, but that an equal Execution of the Laws, might diſcover to us a great ſecret, that the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Part of thoſe who are reputed for Diſſenters, do not ſtand in need of a Toleration; what our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderer ſaies of <hi>reſtering of Trade,</hi> is to ſuggeſt that it is decay'd, whereas it is notoriouſly known, that it never was at a greater height in this Kingdom, than it is at preſent. But when Diſſenters talk of deadneſs of Trade, you muſt underſtand, that the true meaning is only that they are diſcontented, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:101227:34"/>would fain make others ſo low, and becauſe they have no reaſon, or dare not tell the true one, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the ſhame of the World, by uſing a pretence that is notoriouſly falſe.</p>
            <p>The Relation that follows of a cloathier, that was forc'd to leave his Trade and Habitation; and to leave the Poor People he employed upon the Pariſh, and of others of the ſame Trade, that combind to buy no Wool, and to abuſe the Country, to be reveng'd of the Laws, I dare not vouch for true; But ſhould they be all true, which is a very great rarity in the Reports of that Party, I know not what to ſay, but who can help it? Suppoſe that cloathier had broke, for Diſſenters are frail and breakable as other men, and the Poor Workmen had gone a begging. It is a ſad Caſe you will ſay ſo many People ſhould be undone by a ſcurvy Law, that proſecutes men for paying of Debts, or ſuppoſe the man had dy'd, ſome Remedy muſt have been found, and ſome other means to maintain theſe Poor People, there might be more of the Trade that would have been glad of the opportunity of ſucceeding him, for the ſullen men, that abus'd the Country, by combining not to buy, I think they deſerved little favour upon that account, and in ſhort upon this whole vapour of Trade, as if it were wedded only to Diſſenters, it has been anſwered long ago, and thoſe that threatn'd to withdraw their ſtocks were deſir'd, to make their words good, and the King ſufficiently aſſur'd, that the General Trade of the Kingdom ſhould not ſuffer the leaſt diminution, though no one Diſſenter were concern'd in it. However it was then, it is very well known now, that there is a great deal more money in this Kingdom than can be employ'd
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:101227:35"/>in Trade, and we are ſo far from being in a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that obliges us to Court men to proceed in trad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the laying down of Trade, is like the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of an Office, men are not only courted to it, but brib'd and bought to make room for thoſe who are as it were ſhut out of the Exchange, by the extraordinary throng that is within.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſi.</hi> 9. Our Conſideratour tranſcribes ſeveral paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of late his Majeſties Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> and ſome other out of Speeches ſince his Reſtauration, I will not take upon me too anſwer them, but remit the Reader to thoſe Reaſons of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which ſatisfyed the King himſelf, ſo far as to paſs the act of uniformity without any regard had to the Diſſenters, the Declaration for indulgence ſet forth ſome years after, upon better Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was revok'd by the King, but no Council or Parliament were ever able to convince him ſo fully of the Reaſon of putting the Laws in Execution, againſt Diſſenters, as the Diſſenters themſelves, who made at laſt ſuch returns of inſolence and ſedition, for all his indulgence, that he was forc'd for the preſervation of himſelf and his Government, to call for the aſſiſtance of thoſe Laws, and to order them to be put in effectual Execution, and we owe it wholy to his wiſdom and fore-ſight, that ſome of the moſt conſiderable of them are now in being, I mean that of the 35th of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which he ſaved by his Prerogative Law, as well as men when it was condemn'd to be aboliſh'd; And if his clemency had ſaved many, who the Laws had juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned, why ſhould it not ſave a Law, that had done him and his Anceſtours no ſmall ſervice, and was then doom'd to an undeerv'd Fate.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:101227:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſi.</hi> 10. The Tenth and laſt Conſideration, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of ſeveral Teſtimonies, take ſome from Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Eccleſiaſtical Writers, ſome from modern Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, he deals here in Groſs; and is not pleas'd to name his Author from whence he has taken them, that the particulars might be examin'd. It is not impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perhaps to Gueſs, but why ſhould any man break in upon ones private reading, and intrude in his fecret. If our Author had known any other Church Hiſtory, or Collector, it is ten to one but he had choſen better, as for the firſt 800 years, it is true there could not be many Civil Laws againſt Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Chriſtian Religion, yet if our Author had heard of the ſtory of <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Sameſata,</hi> he might have known, that the Civil Power was employ'd in defence of the Catholick Religion againſt Hereſy, even before <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time: He names ſeveral Emperours, with whom I perceive he is unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for I am apt to beleive if he had known any thing of them, he would have left, at leaſtwiſe <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius</hi> and <hi>Vatens,</hi> out of his Catalogue of Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiours, and put in <hi>Julian</hi> who out of pure love and kind neſs to Chriſtian Religion, granted an univerſal. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration to all Sects of diſſenting Chriſtians. <hi>But their larger permiſſion</hi> (he ſays,) <hi>was eſpecially towards Jews.</hi> It may be ſo, for theſe were indulg'd, when ſeveral Chriſtian Sects were not, nay they have a Toleration in almoſt all Chriſtian Kingdoms. And even in <hi>Rome,</hi> where there is ſmall regard had of the Conſciences of Proteſtant Diſſenters, and all this, not becauſe they prefer <hi>Jews</hi> to erring Chriſtians, but becauſe they conceive the Toleration of them, may not have ſo much danger, at that of Chriſtian Sects.</p>
            <p>Yet of theſe Emperours whom he names, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:101227:36"/>proſecuted the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Arnians,</hi> and ſent ſeveral Biſhops that refus'd to ſubſcribe the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Creed into Baniſhment. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Great, and his Sons <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi> did reſtrain many Chriſtian Sects in the Exerciſe of their Conſcience, and ſucceeding Emperours were ſtill more and more ſevere in requiring compliance, with the Religion Eſtabliſh'd in ſeveral Councils.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ithacius,</hi> and <hi>Idacius,</hi> our Author obſerves, <hi>were condem'd by the</hi> Gallican <hi>Biſhops, for being Authors of bringing the</hi> Priſcillianiſts <hi>to Execution:</hi> What Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution I pray? Of Death, they might be juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd for making themſelves Proſecutors, in Caſes of Bloud, but what is all this to our Laws, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of Diſſenters? St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was againſt San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinary Laws in Caſes of Religion, ſo are we; ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Fathers condemn the uſe of all force to bring a man to believe the Goſpell, ſo do we Religion muſt be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and cannot be forc'd ſo ſay we, and yet there may be diſcipline us'd to reduce the wilful &amp; perverſe, and they may be brought the better to ſee their miſtake, by the Inconvenenices it may expoſe them to. The Sects of the <hi>Jews,</hi> were rather in Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, then Religion, for there was no Schiſme nor Breach between them, in regard of the main Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation which the Law requir'd, for they went all into the ſame Temple to Worſhip. The <hi>Joſeptins</hi> would not ſuffer the <hi>Trachonites</hi> to be circumciſed by force, no more do we, either Infidels or their Children to be baptiz'd by force, <hi>Ethelbert</hi> would not compel the Pagan <hi>Saxons</hi> to be come Chriſtians, and <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and <hi>Licinius</hi>'s edict, allows all the Liberty of their Worſhip, becauſe at that time the Circumſtances of Chriſtianity, and Heatheniſm did then require it to be ſo, and yet <hi>Conſtantine</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101227:36"/>ward forbid the Heathen to ſacrifice to their Idols, and ſhut up their Temples. <hi>Bodin</hi> had apoſtatiz'd to Judaiſme, or perhaps Atheiſm, and it is no great matter what he ſays, nor is it of any great Authority, what <hi>Barc-lay</hi> ſays in a Romance, and the Reflexions of Political Writers, when they refine upon any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, are not always wiſe in the practice as wiſe as they are in the Contemplation: Sir E. <hi>Cook</hi> was never againſt the Execution of our Penal Laws againſt Diſſenters, and what Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> ſays is only with reſpect to the time in which they were ſpoken, when it ſeem'd Impoſſible, to make any accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without a General Toleration, but it pleas'd the providence of God to open another way which the wiſeſt men were ſo far from foreſeeing, that they durſt hardly hope it, ſome years before.</p>
            <p>The words of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, had reſpect to the circumſtances of this Kingdom when he wrote, and as for the preamble of the Statute of Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> it is but neceſſary, that thoſe who cannot be brought to love, may be compell'd to fear their Prince, extream puniſhments ſuch as are there intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I believe we have none, and the extreameſt of ours were forced by the Sedition, and not deſign'd againſt the Opinions of Diſſenters, <hi>and if thoſe-juſt Laws, that were made without any extream puniſhment,</hi> had been duly executed, there had in probability been no occaſion for other more ſevere penalties, ſo that if there be any addition of rigor, the Diſſenters muſt thank thoſe that favour'd and conniv'd at them for it, that incourag'd them to be inſolent and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, and forc'd the Government, to take greater ſecurity of a Party that began to grow ungovernable.</p>
            <p>As to the laſt ambiguous Citation, it is ſufficient
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101227:37"/>to reply, that the increaſe of Diſſenters, did always increaſe not only the differences between King and People, and divided their intereſts, but likewiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the intereſt and affections of the People, and therefore whatever way contribute moſt to the growth of a diſaffected Party, cannot be healing, how moderate ſoever it may be, and if the Diſſenters thought they would not thrive better under a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which I cannot ſee any reaſon why they ſhould deſire it.</p>
            <p>And now having return'd this Anſwer to the Queres and conſiderations concerning Toleration, I might from the ſame Topicks that are us'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade to it, proceed to ſhew that ſuch a Toleration as is there demanded, is conſiſtent neither with Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Religion, right reaſon, nor the ſafety and Trade of the Kingdom. For what can be more unchriſtian, than to give wicked, or infatuated men licenſe to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Goſpel, and Blaſpheme the name of Chriſt, under pretence of Religion? What more uncharitable than to give leave to preſumptious men, to confirm themſelves in their own raſh miſtakes, or to ſeduce others into the ſame ſnare of the Devil, <hi>deceiving and being deceiv'd?</hi> What more abſurd or contrary to ſound reaſon, then to give courſe to the moſt extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, the moſt abſurd Opinions under the colour of Religion and Conſcience? And to expoſe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People, who do for the moſt part mean better than they underſtand, to the Practice and Sollicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of every tempting Impoſter, and laſtly what more inconſiſtant with the peace and ſafety of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, than the cheriſhing of a Faction, which has once already overthrown this Monarchy and Church, and engag'd very lately in the ſame deſign? And if
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:101227:37"/>the ſafety of the Government cannot conſiſt with To leration, Trade to be ſure can never ſtrive under it, for Traders will quickly leave a People, whoſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is at the diſcretion of a Faction, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſo much threaten'd with apprehenſions of chang, as to be in probable danger. But I ſhall wave this advantage, being content to keep upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, however it be eſteem'd a part no leſs diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious in controverſie then it is in War, nor is it neceſſary to purſue the debate much farther, ſince it is ſufficient ground for any reaſonable man to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, that the reaſon and the equity of our Laws, are no leſs firm than the Authority by which they were enacted, when the ſhall perceive that all the excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made now againſt them, are either frivolous or falſe, wherefore ſince there are no ſufficient Reaſons alledg'd why the Laws ſhould comply with the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, I will briefly ſuggeſt ſome reaſons why the Diſſenters ſhould comply with the Laws, without entring into the merits of the Cauſe, but keeping my ſelf only to the Principles of the ſeveral Sects; ſo that it muſt needs be highly unreaſonable to plead for a Toleration of ſuch Diſſenters, as might not only lawfully comply with all the Law requires, if their Conſciences were rightly inform'd but may yet comply for the moſt part, even according to the Rule and the Conſcience they profeſs.</p>
            <p>And here I muſt treat with them a part, as they are divided into ſeveral Religious Tribes, and Gonven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, for when they are join'd in one Politick and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Rendezvous, it is no fit place to ſpeak of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And
<list>
                  <item>1. Why ſhould any Presbyterian deſire the Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Conventicles ſhould be repeal'd upon his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101227:38"/>ſince if he have not departed from his firſt Principles, he believes that ſeparation from our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is not only unneceſſary but unlawful. Several of the old <hi>Puritans,</hi> from whom our Presbyterians own their deſcent, have written as zealouſly againſt Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the erecting of diſſenting Congregrations as any of the Divines of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Some of them indeed pretend that they go to Conventicles for greater Edification, but how can that be more edifying, that according to their Principles is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? They may by the ſame way of reaſoning, knock an old heavy teacher on the head, to make way for another that may be more powerful, and edifying. Therefore ſince a Presbyterian Conventicle, is as much a contradiction to the Principle and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Presbyterians, as to the Law of the Land, why ſhould any body interceed for a Toleration of that, which their Principles diſallow?</item>
                  <item>2. Why ſhould any Presbyterian deſire Toleration for not coming to our Churches, ſince by their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples it is not unlawful to hold occaſional Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with our Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſome time to join with us in Common Prayer, and the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, the laſt, and ſtricteſt Bond of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion which Chriſtians hold, and they have been hitherto very much to ſeek for reaſons, why that Communion may not be as lawful to be us'd conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it is upon occaſions, the moſt plauſible excuſe they make is this, that they had Paſtors of their own before the Re-eſtabliſhment, of our Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tho' they may occaſionally communicate with us, as thoſe of one Pariſh may go to a Neighbouring Church upon occaſion, yet they cannot do it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, becauſe of their Antecedent Obligation to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:101227:38"/>their own Paſtors. This excuſe, if it were admitted, would not ſerve half the turn, for if this had any force, why ſhould it not have been admitted in the cauſe of thoſe Miniſters that were turn'd out illegally, to make Room for the Presbyterians? Why were theſe Loyal Miniſters deſerted by the Presbyterians of thoſe days, when they were forc'd by uſurp'd power from the exerciſe of their Function. Beſides there are but few of ſuch Miniſters now living, ſo that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe ſerves but very few Presbyterian Aſſemblies, and there are fewer yet upon the places where they were Miniſters in the time of the late Rebellion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that relation ceaſes, which this excuſe does ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; for why ſhould a company of Presbyterians in <hi>London,</hi> join themſelves to one that taught in <hi>Hull</hi> or <hi>York,</hi> or perhaps in <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon this pretence that they ought not to forſake their former Miniſters? So this can be no excuſe why that occaſional Communion which the Presbyterians profeſs lawful to hold with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould not be improv'd into a conſtant one; therefore there is no need of Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for thoſe who by their own Principle may Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with us upon occaſion, eſpecially the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an Office, for which they are to be qualify'd by ſuch Communion.</item>
                  <item>3. The Independants indeed hold a neceſſity of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating from our, and all other Churches that are not of their form, and ſo their Principles render their compliance with ſome of our Laws more impractica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Yet they have no reaſon to deſire a Toleration for Conventicles, ſince thoſe that the Law makes ſuch are not neceſſary to them according to their own Principles. For The notion they have of a Church, makes ſuch
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:101227:39"/>Conventicles as the Law puniſhes to be unneceſſary, for <hi>Robinſon</hi> affirms, that where two or three peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are gathered there is a Church. <hi>Cotton</hi> requires a few more to make up the integrity of an Organick Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> 7, or 8. Now the Law makes no Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly to be a Conventicle that has not near this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, beſides the Perſons of the Family, where this Meeting is held. Therefore, if the Law puniſh Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Conventicles of greater numbers, it cannot truly be ſaid that they are perſecuted for Conſcience, for that which the Law makes their Crime, <hi>i. e.</hi> their exceeding ſuch a number, is a thing in their own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion unneceſſary.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. If they cannot join with us in Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet they may come to hear our Sermons, as well as thoſe of the Presbyterians, which they hear occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally, ſince no Principle of their Religion forbids it, and they require it in New <hi>England,</hi> of thoſe who are not of their Church; and there is no reaſon they ſhould have any Indulgence in ſuch things as a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inform'd Conſcience makes neceſſary to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſhew themſelves willing to comply with the Law in every thing wherein their Conſcience will give them leave.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Our Anabaptiſts, being of near kin to the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants, and having the ſame notions in a manner with them, concerning the neceſſity and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a Church; are concluded, by the ſame things as have been offer'd, againſt the Toleration of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Conventicles.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But of all Sects the <hi>Quakers</hi> have the leaſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to deſire Toleration for their meetings, becauſe they have not only caſt away the uſe of all Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but alſo of reading and Interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:101227:39"/>in their Aſſemblies. They profeſs to be guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Spirit, <hi>i. e.</hi> Every one by his own, and that they have no other Guide or Teacher, but that Spirit that is within them. Wherefore they uſually apply that Prophecy to themſelves Litterally, <hi>They ſhall not teach every one his Neighbour, nor every one his Brother, ſaying, know the Lord: For they ſhall know the Lord from the leaſt to the greateſt.</hi> Wherefore if there is to be no outward teaching, why do they teach in their meetings? Or to what purpoſe is it to teach there, where either every man is inſpir'd with the Spirit of God, and ſo needs no teaching, or elſe can reap no Benefit by any thing that is ſaid, becauſe he has not the Spirit, without which he cannot be taught? Beſides, what uſe is there of ſilent meetings, where there is nothing at all ſaid? If they have any promiſe of the Spirit, to be inſpir'd in theſe meetings, how comes it to fail? If they have not, why do they meet? The Spirit of the Apoſtles was never want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on any publick occaſion, and we read of no Aſſembly of their time without Prayer, or Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: But the Spirit of the Quakers is of another ſort, ſometimes dumb, ſuch as Chriſt us'd to caſt out. And there is little Reaſon there ſhould be any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe for publick meeting of Perſons only to gape, and groan in an uncertain expectation of being inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and ſince every one by thoſe Enthuſiaſts is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Light within him, the moſt proper place, one would think for ſuch dreamers, is a ſolitary and dark place, for they can attend better to that inward Light, that private Spirit, by Meditation, and turning their thoughts inwardly, than under the variety of application, that commonly diſtract mens thoughts in Publick Aſſemblies.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:101227:40"/>
            <p>There are ſome other Sects among us, very earneſt for Toleration, who have as little need of it, in that Part that regards their Aſſembling for Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as any of the former, and thoſe eſpecially whoſe ſervice is perform'd in a Language they do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, have the leaſt need of a Publick Aſſembly; for if a mans underſtanding be abſent from what is done, it does not import how far off the thing is from his preſence, for he is as far from me to all intents of Benefit, that is out of the reach of my underſtanding, as he that is wholly out of my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a Maſs that is ſaid in <hi>Rome,</hi> may do me as much good by the Intention of the Prieſt there, as one at which I may be preſent, where I underſtand nothing but am only comprehended in the general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>pro papulo Ciroumſtante.</hi> Beſides, the practice of men telling over their Beads in the Publick Worſhip, declares that they belong not to it, and have no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for it, for they cannot in any ſenſe be ſaid to be at the ſame ſervice, who do not join in the ſame Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. If while the Prieſt ſays <hi>Domine non ſum dignus,</hi> I ſay a <hi>Pater,</hi> and another an <hi>Ave,</hi> and a third an <hi>Ora pro Nobis,</hi> this is no more one ſervice, than it is a Harmony when every one ſings or plays what comes in his ſancy, without regarding the Tune or the Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras of any of his Fellow Minſtrels, whereas if they were ſeparated every man apart, might make ſome kind of Muſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When there was no King</hi> in Iſrael, <hi>every man did that which was right in his own Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nevertheleſs the dimneſs ſhall not be ſuch as was in her vexation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Law and the Teſtimony, if they ſpeak not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
